<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-02-17T11:45:15+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">KITAB Project</title><subtitle>Knowledge, Information Technology, and the Arabic Book - Studying the formation and development of the written Arabic tradition with digital methods</subtitle><author><name>{&quot;name&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;avatar&quot;=&gt;&quot;/images/kitab/logo-small-2.png&quot;, &quot;bio&quot;=&gt;&quot;Standing for, Knowledge, Information Technology, and the Arabic Book, KITAB is a project that provides a digital tool-box and a forum for discussions about Arabic texts. We wish to empower users to explore Arabic texts in completely new ways and to expand the frontiers of knowledge about one of the world’s largest and most complex textual traditions. We are leading with a tool that detects how authors copied previous works. Arabic authors frequently made use of past works, cutting them into pieces and reconstituting them to address their own outlooks and concerns. Now you can discover relationships between these texts and also the profoundly intertextual circulatory systems in which they sit.&quot;, &quot;location&quot;=&gt;&quot;AKU, London, UK&quot;, &quot;email&quot;=&gt;&quot;sarah.savant@aku.edu&quot;, &quot;uri&quot;=&gt;nil, &quot;flickr&quot;=&gt;nil, &quot;facebook&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;, &quot;github&quot;=&gt;&quot;https://github.com/kitab-project-org/&quot;, &quot;google_plus&quot;=&gt;nil, &quot;instagram&quot;=&gt;nil, &quot;linkedin&quot;=&gt;nil, &quot;pinterest&quot;=&gt;nil, &quot;soundcloud&quot;=&gt;nil, &quot;stackoverflow&quot;=&gt;nil, &quot;steam&quot;=&gt;nil, &quot;tumblr&quot;=&gt;nil, &quot;twitter&quot;=&gt;&quot;&quot;}</name><email>sarah.savant@aku.edu</email></author><entry><title type="html">Diversifying the OpenITI corpus, One Text at a Time</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01-21.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Diversifying the OpenITI corpus, One Text at a Time" /><published>2021-01-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/Diversifying%20the%20OpenITI%20corpus,%20One%20Text%20at%20a%20Time</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01-21.html">&lt;p&gt;The vast majority of texts in the OpenITI corpus were sourced from three major collections of digital texts originally prepared by organisations based in the Middle East (see Peter Verkinderen’s excellent blog on the largest of them, &lt;a href=&quot;http://kitab-project.org/2020/12/03/al-maktaba-al-shamila-a-short-history/&quot;&gt;Shamela&lt;/a&gt;). These collections have proven invaluable to researchers, not in the least because they have facilitated digital forms of analysis, but they all made choices about which textual materials should belong on their platforms and which should not. Shamela for example did not originally include any poetry and focused largely on Sunni traditionalism. Another significant omission in each of these collections is the rich corpus of Arabic texts written by and for non-Muslims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it would be naive to think that OpenITI is itself unbiased, we do aim to be as inclusive as possible and try to address several of the issues found in other collections. First, we bring the separate collections together and engage all of them in a continuous dialogue on text reuse. Second, we identify and try to fill gaps in the corpus through digitising texts ourselves or through collaborating with other research teams. This has led to the inclusion of texts digitised by other academic projects in fields that are of only marginal interest to the major text collections. Due to the concerted efforts of Peter Verkinderen and Lorenz Nigst, we now have a number of agrarian treatises, Greco-Arabic philosophical materials, texts of ancient wisdom, as well as some materials preserved in the so-called Cairo Geniza. We list all these various collections and individual contributors with their URI identifiers &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenITI/Annotation&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, I have also contributed a number of texts I am interested in by using Optical Character Recognition software, typing up manuscript treatises, and by contacting people who published texts online. To encourage people to also contribute such materials they may have to our corpus, I will here briefly describe a small set of texts I have contributed to the OpenITI in this way. If readers of this blog feel inclined to contribute textual materials in exchange for text reuse data, they should get in contact with KITAB team members and we will happily accept their offers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/old_posts/Gowaart-Blog-pic-1024x768.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some time ago I was researching historical accounts about a Mamluk expedition against the Nusayri-ʿAlawis in the Lebanese Kisrawan region (the rugged mountain terrain north and northeast of Beirut) which took place in 704/1304. To my pleasant surprise, I found a number of Maronite sources who discuss these events. One of these was a type of text I had not encountered before in my readings of Arabic literature: an epic poem in the z&lt;em&gt;ajaliyya&lt;/em&gt; form written by the Maronite bishop Jibraʾil Ibn al-Qilaʿi (d. 921/1516). Ibn al-Qilaʿi had been instrumental in spreading adherence to the Catholic Pope amongst Maronites in the region of present-day Lebanon, and thus strengthening the full communion with Rome which the Maronite Church still follows. The poem is usually designated as &lt;em&gt;Madiha fi Jabal Lubnan.&lt;/em&gt; and describes events of heroic resistance against outsiders by Maronite chiefs from the dawn of time up to his own day. It consists of 294 quatrains of which the first three hemistiches rhyme with each other and the fourth ends on a monorhyme sustained throughout the entire poem. While there are many Arabic poems discussing or commenting on historical events, they do not tend to be narrative in the way an epic poem usually is. Ibn al-Qilaʿi’s work, by contrast, is highly narrative, if not in a linear chronological way. Furthermore, Ibn al-Qilaʿi’s introductory verses express some interesting ideas about time, history and memory which I am hoping to unpack more in further research. Consider for example this quatrain which seems to conceive of an important role for poets in preserving cultural memory:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
وكيف العصور بتتغير   \*   وفيها العقول بتتحير  \*  ولولا توجد في الاسطار  
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
 ما كان يخبر عنه انسان
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
How the ages change
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
while intellects get confused
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
if it weren’t for you finding in the lines of text
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
what informs man about himself


&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of its relatively short length I decided to digitise this poem by using Google’s OCR engine which can be used via Google Drive. The added personal benefit is that by post-correcting the digital text I am effectively skim reading it as a whole, familiarising myself with its structure and identifying interesting sections to return to in more detail. Ibn al-Qilaʿi’s text was edited by Bulus Qaraʾli in 1937 as part of his book &lt;em&gt;Hurub al-muqaddamin&lt;/em&gt; (“The Wars of the [Maronite] Commanders”)&lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; a blend of primary texts and commentary by Qaraʾli on the Maronite community’s vicissitudes in dealing with their surroundings across the ages. Because of this hybrid publication form, digitising this edition posed a number of challenges and obliged me to make some editorial choices. We always record these kinds of decisions in a so-called YML-file, a specific format of markup language which we use to record various forms of metadata in a formalised and computer-readable way. We use three forms of such files: one for author metadata (which includes an author’s birth and death date, various geographical locations, as well as personal relationships), one for general book metadata (including a.o. variant titles and relationships to other books), and one for version metadata. Below is an example of my version metadata for Ibn al-Qilaʿi’s &lt;em&gt;Madiha&lt;/em&gt;: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;00#VERS#CLENGTH##: 20224&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;00#VERS#LENGTH###: 4673&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;00#VERS#URI######: 0921JibrailIbnQilaci.MadihaFiJabalLubnan.GVDB20200821-ara1&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;80#VERS#BASED####: http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/784489194&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;80#VERS#COLLATED#: http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/784489194&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;80#VERS#LINKS####: https://www.noor-book.com/كتاب-حروب-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;    المقدمين-1075-1450-pdf-1593183859&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;90#VERS#ANNOTATOR: Gowaart Van Den Bossche&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;90#VERS#COMMENT##: &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;This text was digitised with Google OCR and corrected by Gowaart. I have followed the edition's lack of consistently noting the hamza and using a generic ha instead of ta marbuta. The edition of the text is somewhat complicated. It interlaces the poem included here with a 19th-century anonymous mukhtasar (see Salibi, &quot;Maronite Historians of Medieval Lebanon&quot;, p. 39) as well as a commentary by the editor. For OpenITI purposes I felt it was best to separate these three layers, and assign separate URIs to the poem and the mukhtasar, while deleting the editorial commentary. I have also deleted the titles, as these seem to be part of the commentary rather than the poem. As a result the pagination looks like the text has gaps, but this is entirely due to my reorganisation of the texts.  The poem is a zajaliyya in Lebanese colloquial. This poetic form is in quatrains, as opposed to the usual Arabic two hemistiches. Currently mARkdown does not accommodate this form (in which the first three hemistiches rhyme with one another, while the last hemistich follows the endrhyme of each other quatrain in the poem), so I have followed some other editors of other texts by splitting the quatrain into two parts. This way it looks identical to other Arabic poetry, except that the end rhyme only happens every two lines.&lt;/code&gt; 90#VERS#DATE#####: 2020-08-21&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;90#VERS#ISSUES###: NO_MAJOR_ISSUES&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See Hamidreza’s blog for another example of a YML file and some discussion of how it should be used within the &lt;a href=&quot;http://kitab-project.org/2020/06/12/tagging-the-structure-of-texts-in-the-openiti-corpus/&quot;&gt;OpenITI annotation process&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having grown interested in Ibn al-Qilaʿi (a more malignant observer might say I fell down a substantial rabbit hole) I did some further research and stumbled upon the Academia page of the Lebanese cleric P. Elie Saade. He had edited a few &lt;em&gt;zajaliyya&lt;/em&gt;s he found in manuscripts across his home country and published them on his page. I contacted him directly to ask whether he would want to contribute his editions to the OpenITI, something he happily agreed to do. As such, we were able to add one more poem written by Ibn al-Qilaʿi (a hagiography of the third century saint Mar Nuhra) to our corpus, as well as a 19th-century &lt;em&gt;zajaliyya&lt;/em&gt; by a Lebanese priest. Saade had transcribed both of these into Arabic script from the Karshuni (Arabic in Syriac script) originals in which they have been preserved. He has also since then notified me of another &lt;em&gt;zajaliyya&lt;/em&gt; he published which deals with the experience of the First World War in Lebanon. I hope to add this text to the corpus in the near future. You can find the OpenITI versions of the two first texts on the links below. Note the PES+date at the end of the URI, this identifies P. Elie Saade as contributor to the corpus. Note also that in the above-cited YML file the URI bears my initials GVDB as I was the one who digitised this text through OCR. In this way we keep track of the diverse origins of text versions in our corpus while harmonising their contents as much as possible. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenITI/0925AH/tree/master/data/0921JibrailIbnQilaci/0921JibrailIbnQilaci.QissatMarNuhra&quot;&gt;0921JibrailIbnQilaci.QissatMarNuhra.PES20201020-ara1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenITI/1350AH/tree/master/data/1337IstifanThani/1337IstifanThani.Zajaliyya&quot;&gt;1337IstifanThani.Zajaliyya.PES20201021-ara1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through such additions our corpus becomes a little more balanced, but these are of course only small steps towards capturing the true diversity of the Arabic written tradition. There is still a lot of work to be done to achieve a more rounded balance in the corpus. Indeed, three new Christian Arabic texts within a corpus of some 5,000 individual texts is but a drop in an Islamic ocean. It will also come as no surprise that neither of these three texts showcases a lot (if any) reuse. The one case of reuse identified by passim for Ibn al-Qilaʿi is from a late 19th-century compendium of Christian Arabic texts compiled by the great Jesuit Chaldean Catholic scholar Louis Cheikho (d. 1927), in which a number of verses from the &lt;em&gt;Madiha&lt;/em&gt; are directly quoted. Even fully capturing the relatively minor &lt;em&gt;zajaliyya&lt;/em&gt; tradition poses further challenges. Because they are generally seen as of limited literary value (Kamal Salibi called Ibn al-Qilaʿi’s poems “dull”) and because of their highly regional character, only very few of these texts have been edited and published. As noted, the majority only exist in manuscripts written in Karshuni, so they require people fluent in both scripts to properly transcribe and edit them. They are also largely written in colloquial Arabic. This issue of script and language is another aspect we would like our metadata to reflect better, especially as more Geniza materials (much of which is written in Judaeo-Arabic, that is, Arabic written in Hebrew script) will be added to the corpus in the future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I wanted to highlight more generally is that pooling the various resources of Arabic texts increasingly available online into one harmonised corpus is all well and good, but if we want to really remedy major gaps and issues we also need concerted efforts from scholars to identify gaps in the corpus, as well as to actively curate and contribute materials. Here are a few ways in which you can get involved:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you notice relevant texts/genres/… are missing in our corpus, we can show you how to add these texts yourself (or you can simply notify us that we should include them, especially if you can propose a way to acquire them in digital format).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you are a specialist, you could become a curator for texts for your field, identifying gaps, creating lists of texts to be digitized, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Inform us about other projects that have digitized texts that may not be in our corpus.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bibliography&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most comprehensive treatment of Ibn al-Qilaʿi remains K.S. Salibi, &lt;em&gt;Maronite Historians of Medieval Lebanon&lt;/em&gt; (Beirut 1959).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The photograph used in this blog was taken by Gowaart in May 2017 in one of the Maronite monasteries in the beautiful Kadisha Valley below Bsharré in North Lebanon.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Gowaart Van Den Bossche</name></author><summary type="html">The vast majority of texts in the OpenITI corpus were sourced from three major collections of digital texts originally prepared by organisations based in the Middle East (see Peter Verkinderen’s excellent blog on the largest of them, Shamela). These collections have proven invaluable to researchers, not in the least because they have facilitated digital forms of analysis, but they all made choices about which textual materials should belong on their platforms and which should not. Shamela for example did not originally include any poetry and focused largely on Sunni traditionalism. Another significant omission in each of these collections is the rich corpus of Arabic texts written by and for non-Muslims. While it would be naive to think that OpenITI is itself unbiased, we do aim to be as inclusive as possible and try to address several of the issues found in other collections. First, we bring the separate collections together and engage all of them in a continuous dialogue on text reuse. Second, we identify and try to fill gaps in the corpus through digitising texts ourselves or through collaborating with other research teams. This has led to the inclusion of texts digitised by other academic projects in fields that are of only marginal interest to the major text collections. Due to the concerted efforts of Peter Verkinderen and Lorenz Nigst, we now have a number of agrarian treatises, Greco-Arabic philosophical materials, texts of ancient wisdom, as well as some materials preserved in the so-called Cairo Geniza. We list all these various collections and individual contributors with their URI identifiers here. In the meantime, I have also contributed a number of texts I am interested in by using Optical Character Recognition software, typing up manuscript treatises, and by contacting people who published texts online. To encourage people to also contribute such materials they may have to our corpus, I will here briefly describe a small set of texts I have contributed to the OpenITI in this way. If readers of this blog feel inclined to contribute textual materials in exchange for text reuse data, they should get in contact with KITAB team members and we will happily accept their offers. Some time ago I was researching historical accounts about a Mamluk expedition against the Nusayri-ʿAlawis in the Lebanese Kisrawan region (the rugged mountain terrain north and northeast of Beirut) which took place in 704/1304. To my pleasant surprise, I found a number of Maronite sources who discuss these events. One of these was a type of text I had not encountered before in my readings of Arabic literature: an epic poem in the zajaliyya form written by the Maronite bishop Jibraʾil Ibn al-Qilaʿi (d. 921/1516). Ibn al-Qilaʿi had been instrumental in spreading adherence to the Catholic Pope amongst Maronites in the region of present-day Lebanon, and thus strengthening the full communion with Rome which the Maronite Church still follows. The poem is usually designated as Madiha fi Jabal Lubnan. and describes events of heroic resistance against outsiders by Maronite chiefs from the dawn of time up to his own day. It consists of 294 quatrains of which the first three hemistiches rhyme with each other and the fourth ends on a monorhyme sustained throughout the entire poem. While there are many Arabic poems discussing or commenting on historical events, they do not tend to be narrative in the way an epic poem usually is. Ibn al-Qilaʿi’s work, by contrast, is highly narrative, if not in a linear chronological way. Furthermore, Ibn al-Qilaʿi’s introductory verses express some interesting ideas about time, history and memory which I am hoping to unpack more in further research. Consider for example this quatrain which seems to conceive of an important role for poets in preserving cultural memory: وكيف العصور بتتغير   \*   وفيها العقول بتتحير  \*  ولولا توجد في الاسطار    ما كان يخبر عنه انسان How the ages change while intellects get confused if it weren’t for you finding in the lines of text what informs man about himself Because of its relatively short length I decided to digitise this poem by using Google’s OCR engine which can be used via Google Drive. The added personal benefit is that by post-correcting the digital text I am effectively skim reading it as a whole, familiarising myself with its structure and identifying interesting sections to return to in more detail. Ibn al-Qilaʿi’s text was edited by Bulus Qaraʾli in 1937 as part of his book Hurub al-muqaddamin (“The Wars of the [Maronite] Commanders”), a blend of primary texts and commentary by Qaraʾli on the Maronite community’s vicissitudes in dealing with their surroundings across the ages. Because of this hybrid publication form, digitising this edition posed a number of challenges and obliged me to make some editorial choices. We always record these kinds of decisions in a so-called YML-file, a specific format of markup language which we use to record various forms of metadata in a formalised and computer-readable way. We use three forms of such files: one for author metadata (which includes an author’s birth and death date, various geographical locations, as well as personal relationships), one for general book metadata (including a.o. variant titles and relationships to other books), and one for version metadata. Below is an example of my version metadata for Ibn al-Qilaʿi’s Madiha:  00#VERS#CLENGTH##: 20224 00#VERS#LENGTH###: 4673 00#VERS#URI######: 0921JibrailIbnQilaci.MadihaFiJabalLubnan.GVDB20200821-ara1 80#VERS#BASED####: http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/784489194 80#VERS#COLLATED#: http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/784489194 80#VERS#LINKS####: https://www.noor-book.com/كتاب-حروب-     المقدمين-1075-1450-pdf-1593183859 90#VERS#ANNOTATOR: Gowaart Van Den Bossche 90#VERS#COMMENT##: This text was digitised with Google OCR and corrected by Gowaart. I have followed the edition's lack of consistently noting the hamza and using a generic ha instead of ta marbuta. The edition of the text is somewhat complicated. It interlaces the poem included here with a 19th-century anonymous mukhtasar (see Salibi, &quot;Maronite Historians of Medieval Lebanon&quot;, p. 39) as well as a commentary by the editor. For OpenITI purposes I felt it was best to separate these three layers, and assign separate URIs to the poem and the mukhtasar, while deleting the editorial commentary. I have also deleted the titles, as these seem to be part of the commentary rather than the poem. As a result the pagination looks like the text has gaps, but this is entirely due to my reorganisation of the texts.  The poem is a zajaliyya in Lebanese colloquial. This poetic form is in quatrains, as opposed to the usual Arabic two hemistiches. Currently mARkdown does not accommodate this form (in which the first three hemistiches rhyme with one another, while the last hemistich follows the endrhyme of each other quatrain in the poem), so I have followed some other editors of other texts by splitting the quatrain into two parts. This way it looks identical to other Arabic poetry, except that the end rhyme only happens every two lines. 90#VERS#DATE#####: 2020-08-21 90#VERS#ISSUES###: NO_MAJOR_ISSUES See Hamidreza’s blog for another example of a YML file and some discussion of how it should be used within the OpenITI annotation process.  Having grown interested in Ibn al-Qilaʿi (a more malignant observer might say I fell down a substantial rabbit hole) I did some further research and stumbled upon the Academia page of the Lebanese cleric P. Elie Saade. He had edited a few zajaliyyas he found in manuscripts across his home country and published them on his page. I contacted him directly to ask whether he would want to contribute his editions to the OpenITI, something he happily agreed to do. As such, we were able to add one more poem written by Ibn al-Qilaʿi (a hagiography of the third century saint Mar Nuhra) to our corpus, as well as a 19th-century zajaliyya by a Lebanese priest. Saade had transcribed both of these into Arabic script from the Karshuni (Arabic in Syriac script) originals in which they have been preserved. He has also since then notified me of another zajaliyya he published which deals with the experience of the First World War in Lebanon. I hope to add this text to the corpus in the near future. You can find the OpenITI versions of the two first texts on the links below. Note the PES+date at the end of the URI, this identifies P. Elie Saade as contributor to the corpus. Note also that in the above-cited YML file the URI bears my initials GVDB as I was the one who digitised this text through OCR. In this way we keep track of the diverse origins of text versions in our corpus while harmonising their contents as much as possible.  0921JibrailIbnQilaci.QissatMarNuhra.PES20201020-ara1 1337IstifanThani.Zajaliyya.PES20201021-ara1 Through such additions our corpus becomes a little more balanced, but these are of course only small steps towards capturing the true diversity of the Arabic written tradition. There is still a lot of work to be done to achieve a more rounded balance in the corpus. Indeed, three new Christian Arabic texts within a corpus of some 5,000 individual texts is but a drop in an Islamic ocean. It will also come as no surprise that neither of these three texts showcases a lot (if any) reuse. The one case of reuse identified by passim for Ibn al-Qilaʿi is from a late 19th-century compendium of Christian Arabic texts compiled by the great Jesuit Chaldean Catholic scholar Louis Cheikho (d. 1927), in which a number of verses from the Madiha are directly quoted. Even fully capturing the relatively minor zajaliyya tradition poses further challenges. Because they are generally seen as of limited literary value (Kamal Salibi called Ibn al-Qilaʿi’s poems “dull”) and because of their highly regional character, only very few of these texts have been edited and published. As noted, the majority only exist in manuscripts written in Karshuni, so they require people fluent in both scripts to properly transcribe and edit them. They are also largely written in colloquial Arabic. This issue of script and language is another aspect we would like our metadata to reflect better, especially as more Geniza materials (much of which is written in Judaeo-Arabic, that is, Arabic written in Hebrew script) will be added to the corpus in the future.  What I wanted to highlight more generally is that pooling the various resources of Arabic texts increasingly available online into one harmonised corpus is all well and good, but if we want to really remedy major gaps and issues we also need concerted efforts from scholars to identify gaps in the corpus, as well as to actively curate and contribute materials. Here are a few ways in which you can get involved: If you notice relevant texts/genres/… are missing in our corpus, we can show you how to add these texts yourself (or you can simply notify us that we should include them, especially if you can propose a way to acquire them in digital format). If you are a specialist, you could become a curator for texts for your field, identifying gaps, creating lists of texts to be digitized, and so on. Inform us about other projects that have digitized texts that may not be in our corpus. Bibliography The most comprehensive treatment of Ibn al-Qilaʿi remains K.S. Salibi, Maronite Historians of Medieval Lebanon (Beirut 1959). The photograph used in this blog was taken by Gowaart in May 2017 in one of the Maronite monasteries in the beautiful Kadisha Valley below Bsharré in North Lebanon.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Tracing the origins of a historical fragment focused on the Sāmānids</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12-11.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Tracing the origins of a historical fragment focused on the Sāmānids" /><published>2020-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/Tracing%20the%20origins%20of%20a%20historical%20fragment%20focused%20on%20the%20S%C4%81m%C4%81nids</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12-11.html">&lt;p&gt;At the Arabic Pasts conference this year, Hugh Kennedy and I presented a paper in the panel dedicated to the Invisible East program, chaired by the program’s PI Arezou Azad. The paper focused on a fragment from an as-yet-unknown Arabic historical text, focused on the Sāmānid dynasty of the 4th/10th century. The fragment is one of the manuscripts from the Bamiyan region of Afghanistan that were recently acquired by the National Library of Israel (the shelfmarks for the bifolios that comprise the fragment are Heb. 8333.190=4 and Heb. 8333.191=4). This is among the very few literary texts, in Arabic, in this corpus; otherwise, it mostly consists of legal documents and letters in Persian. We plan to edit and publish this fragment in full, along with a translation and commentary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The text is written in a bookhand typical of the 10th or 11th century CE, with certain features, most notably its inconsistent numbers of lines from page to page, that suggest it was a kind of draft. In several places, direct witnesses to the events described are cited, suggesting that that the text’s author was not far from these events either, in time or space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fragment seems likely to come from a text that is otherwise no longer extant. We illustrated this point through an in-depth look at a passage in the fragment treating the succession dispute following the murder of the Sāmānid amīr Aḥmad ibn Ismāʿīl in 301/914, and a comparison with the treatments of these events in the other major sources on the Sāmānids. The passage in question includes a long speech by the (eventual) Sāmānid vizier Jayhānī, as he exhorts Aḥmad’s retinue of slave-soldiers to rally behind Aḥmad’s young son Naṣr b. Aḥmad. This Jayhānī is also known for his geographical scholarship and for being a bit of a neat freak (relatable in these times). According to Ibn Ẓāfir, writing in the late 12th or early 13th century CE, “when he passed a veterinarian treating a dog, he became overwhelmed by disgust and pushed his hand out of his sleeve, keeping it in this position until he reached his home, where he poured pitcher after pitcher of water on it.”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In the speech, Jayhānī rebukes these men for caring too much about money, and not enough about their duties to the son of their murdered lord, but deftly adds that they will also be remunerated very well indeed for their troubles. He tells them they will receive a special bonus, in addition to their regular salaries, when Naṣr b. Aḥmad formally succeeds his father.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the author’s familiarity with the city of Bukhara, and closeness to the events described, it seems possible that what we have is from the original Arabic text of Narshakhī’s (d. unknown) &lt;em&gt;History of Bukhara&lt;/em&gt;, which otherwise only exists in an abridged Persian translation from 522/1128, but more work is required to say for sure. In any event, we can be fairly sure that the text does not correspond to any known text in Arabic. The KITAB team ran a transcription of the manuscript (made by Kosar Mirrazi) through its text re-use software package and found no matches, which further supports our theory that this text has no surviving precedent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/old_posts/image.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A folio from MS Heb. 8333.191=4, housed at the National Library of Israel. The image is from the full catalogue entry, which can be accessed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nli.org.il/en/manuscripts/NNL_ALEPH003924972/NLI&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;As translated by Luke Treadwell (The Account of the Samanid Dynasty in Ibn Ẓāfir Al-Azdī’s Akhbār al-Duwal al-Munqaṭiʿa.” &lt;em&gt;Iran&lt;/em&gt; 43: 135–71, p. 156) &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Thomas Benfey</name></author><summary type="html">At the Arabic Pasts conference this year, Hugh Kennedy and I presented a paper in the panel dedicated to the Invisible East program, chaired by the program’s PI Arezou Azad. The paper focused on a fragment from an as-yet-unknown Arabic historical text, focused on the Sāmānid dynasty of the 4th/10th century. The fragment is one of the manuscripts from the Bamiyan region of Afghanistan that were recently acquired by the National Library of Israel (the shelfmarks for the bifolios that comprise the fragment are Heb. 8333.190=4 and Heb. 8333.191=4). This is among the very few literary texts, in Arabic, in this corpus; otherwise, it mostly consists of legal documents and letters in Persian. We plan to edit and publish this fragment in full, along with a translation and commentary. The text is written in a bookhand typical of the 10th or 11th century CE, with certain features, most notably its inconsistent numbers of lines from page to page, that suggest it was a kind of draft. In several places, direct witnesses to the events described are cited, suggesting that that the text’s author was not far from these events either, in time or space. The fragment seems likely to come from a text that is otherwise no longer extant. We illustrated this point through an in-depth look at a passage in the fragment treating the succession dispute following the murder of the Sāmānid amīr Aḥmad ibn Ismāʿīl in 301/914, and a comparison with the treatments of these events in the other major sources on the Sāmānids. The passage in question includes a long speech by the (eventual) Sāmānid vizier Jayhānī, as he exhorts Aḥmad’s retinue of slave-soldiers to rally behind Aḥmad’s young son Naṣr b. Aḥmad. This Jayhānī is also known for his geographical scholarship and for being a bit of a neat freak (relatable in these times). According to Ibn Ẓāfir, writing in the late 12th or early 13th century CE, “when he passed a veterinarian treating a dog, he became overwhelmed by disgust and pushed his hand out of his sleeve, keeping it in this position until he reached his home, where he poured pitcher after pitcher of water on it.”1 In the speech, Jayhānī rebukes these men for caring too much about money, and not enough about their duties to the son of their murdered lord, but deftly adds that they will also be remunerated very well indeed for their troubles. He tells them they will receive a special bonus, in addition to their regular salaries, when Naṣr b. Aḥmad formally succeeds his father. Given the author’s familiarity with the city of Bukhara, and closeness to the events described, it seems possible that what we have is from the original Arabic text of Narshakhī’s (d. unknown) History of Bukhara, which otherwise only exists in an abridged Persian translation from 522/1128, but more work is required to say for sure. In any event, we can be fairly sure that the text does not correspond to any known text in Arabic. The KITAB team ran a transcription of the manuscript (made by Kosar Mirrazi) through its text re-use software package and found no matches, which further supports our theory that this text has no surviving precedent. A folio from MS Heb. 8333.191=4, housed at the National Library of Israel. The image is from the full catalogue entry, which can be accessed here. As translated by Luke Treadwell (The Account of the Samanid Dynasty in Ibn Ẓāfir Al-Azdī’s Akhbār al-Duwal al-Munqaṭiʿa.” Iran 43: 135–71, p. 156) &amp;#8617;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Al-Maktaba al-Shāmila: a short history</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12-03.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Al-Maktaba al-Shāmila: a short history" /><published>2020-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/Al-Maktaba%20al-Sh%C4%81mila-%20a%20short%20history</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12-03.html">&lt;h6 id=&quot;this-is-the-first-blog-post-in-a-longer-series-of-posts-about-the-sources-of-openiti&quot;&gt;&lt;sub&gt;(This is the first blog post in a longer series of posts about the sources of OpenITI)&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Al-Maktaba al-Shāmila (“The comprehensive library”, often referred to simply as Shamela) is a free software that aims at providing a digital research environment for Islamic scholars, and comes with a large collection of Arabic primary sources and secondary texts. It has millions of users in the Islamic world, and is also widely used in academia. It is currently the largest source of texts in the OpenITI corpus: about 45% of the texts in the corpus come from Shamela.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In its first iteration, it was called &lt;em&gt;al-mawsūʿa al-shāmila&lt;/em&gt; (“The Comprehensive Encyclopaedia”). The program was created by an Egyptian member of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ahlalhdeeth.com/&quot;&gt;Ahl al-Ḥadīth forum&lt;/a&gt; known only as Nāfiʿ (often referred to affectionately on specialized internet fora as &lt;em&gt;al-akh Nāfiʿ&lt;/em&gt;  “Brother Nāfiʿ” or &lt;em&gt;duktūr / al-ustādh Nāfiʿ&lt;/em&gt; “Dr. Nāfiʿ”). When the program, containing 969 free books, first appeared on internet fora for Islamic scholars in early 2005, it met with a lot of enthusiasm. So much so that the pioneering publishing house of digital texts, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.xn--turth-hwa.com/&quot;&gt;Markaz al-Turāth lil-barāmijāt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (the publisher of al-Jāmiʿ al-Kabīr, that other main source of texts in our corpus), launched an acrimonious attack against the program on the Ahl al-Ḥadīth forum, accusing Nāfiʿ of stealing its software and content. This post led to such a heated discussion that the forum moderators had to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ahlalhdeeth.com/vb//showthread.php?t=30060&quot;&gt;remove&lt;/a&gt; the thread, and ban all content related to al-mawsūʿa al-shāmila on 4 May 2005. A new discussion &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ahlalhdeeth.com/vb/showthread.php?t=30204&quot;&gt;thread&lt;/a&gt; was eventually opened on 7 May, with a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ahlalhdeeth.com/vb//showpost.php?p=157410&amp;amp;postcount=1&quot;&gt;statement&lt;/a&gt; from al-Turāth and a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ahlalhdeeth.com/vb/showpost.php?p=158529&amp;amp;postcount=2&quot;&gt;response&lt;/a&gt; from the forum moderators. In its statement, al-Turāth apologized for their earlier reaction, before explaining in detail why it considered the program an act of theft (of digitized texts and specialized data) that would kill off not only the company but also all industry-led digitization efforts. In their reaction, the forum moderators thanked al-Turāth for their huge service to the field and Islām, but also defended its forum members involved in the creation and distribution of the program as driven only by love for Islam. The discussion lasted for weeks, and eventually prompted Nāfiʿ, the creator of the program himself, to react in a post on the forum. In his &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ahlalhdeeth.com/vb/showpost.php?p=159996&amp;amp;postcount=90&quot;&gt;statement&lt;/a&gt;, he claimed he had developed the program for himself, to enable him to simultaneously search the different collections of digital books all of which he had legally. While admitting these included books from al-Turāth, he strenuously denied that Shamela was “al-Turāth in another jacket”, adducing proof that he had included books and data from many different sources. He claimed not to have shared his program with more than a handful of scholars, and to have been surprised when he noticed, two years later, another member of the Ahl al-Ḥadīth forum, with whom he had not shared the program, and whom he did not even know, offering it (for free) to other members. He also vowed to create a new version of the program that did not include any book taken from a commercial product. After seemingly conciliatory rhetoric from both sides, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ahlalhdeeth.com/vb/showthread.php?t=30204&amp;amp;page=10&quot;&gt;discussion&lt;/a&gt; turned bitter again, resulting in repeated accusations of piracy and calls for a boycott flying in both directions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ahlalhdeeth.com/vb/showpost.php?p=577789&amp;amp;postcount=2&quot;&gt;January 2006&lt;/a&gt; Nāfiʿ finally published the promised second version (&lt;em&gt;al-iṣdār al-thānī&lt;/em&gt;) of the program, under the title &lt;em&gt;al-Maktaba al-Shāmila&lt;/em&gt; (“The Comprehensive Library”). As he had vowed, it did not include material taken (directly) from al-Turāth products, but only from free websites and internet fora. This meant that it could not offer a number of important features of the first version: the page numbers of most texts did not agree with any published edition, and services like identification of ḥadīth transmitters and historical figures, which had been based on databases from al-Turāth, were &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ahlalhdeeth.com/vb/archive/index.php/t-93748.html&quot;&gt;absent&lt;/a&gt;. On the flip side, the program was still free, and contained a much larger number of texts than the first version, ca. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ahlalhdeeth.com/vb/showpost.php?p=577789&amp;amp;postcount=2&quot;&gt;1800 books&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to a greatly increased collection of digitized books, the most important &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ahlalhdeeth.com/vb/showpost.php?p=577789&amp;amp;postcount=2&quot;&gt;feature&lt;/a&gt; of the second version was that it was the first program of its kind that offered the user the possibility to import their own texts into the program so they could create their own personal library. At the same time, this opened the door for people to keep using the program for reading and searching texts from companies like al-Turāth, without Shamela having to take responsibility for this. Shamela was the first program of its kind to offer this kind of feature, and it probably played an important role in its great success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using this feature, a number of groups and individuals started publishing their own versions of al-Maktaba al-Shāmila with many additional texts (e.g., the augmented Shamela collection of Islamport.com contained already 3.300 books in &lt;a href=&quot;https://ahlalhdeeth.com/vb//showpost.php?p=513459&amp;amp;postcount=1&quot;&gt;September 2006&lt;/a&gt; and more than 5.000 books in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ahlalhdeeth.com/vb/archive/index.php/t-87956.html&quot;&gt;March 2007&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oceanofislam.co.uk/golden-shamela.html&quot;&gt;al-Maktaba al-Shāmila al-Dhahabiyya&lt;/a&gt; contained 29.000 books in 2019). A number of these apocryphal shamela collections were created by groups from a minority (non-Sunnī) Islamic community (e.g., &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.anazaidi.com/catsmktba-78.html&quot;&gt;al-Maktaba al-Zaydiyya al-Shāmila&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.org/details/5_20190723&quot;&gt;al-Maktaba al-Shāmila al-Ibāḍiyya&lt;/a&gt;), whose books were not represented in the main Shamela collection. We will discuss these unofficial shamela collections in a later blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first, Shamela Version 2 was distributed via internet fora, as was the first version: due to limited stable internet access and bandwidth in much of the world at that time. The book collection was downloadable from a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ahlalhdeeth.com/vb/showthread.php?t=70719&quot;&gt;variety&lt;/a&gt; of internet fora and file sharing websites (including the then very recent website &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20060226101151/http://www.waqfeya.net/shamela/&quot;&gt;waqfeya.net&lt;/a&gt;); and users were &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ahlalhdeeth.com/vb/showthread.php?t=70555&quot;&gt;encouraged&lt;/a&gt; to share copies of the program on CDs with people who did not have stable internet access.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third version, released on &lt;a href=&quot;https://shamela.ws/index.php/page/about-shamela&quot;&gt;3 June 2008&lt;/a&gt;, represented an audacious step: Shamela &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20080828033953/https://www.shamela.ws/help.php?do=new3&quot;&gt;decided&lt;/a&gt; to create a dedicated collection of books of its own that recreated the features lost in the second version after the dispute with al-Turāth. Books from this official Shamela collection would have page numbers that agreed with the printed editions, and would enable special features like a &lt;em&gt;takhrīj&lt;/em&gt; function for ḥadīth works (which would identify the sources for a ḥadīth). However, the user would still be able to use the program for both the official collection and external books (using an improved import mechanism). An additional well-received feature was that both official and external books could be linked to scanned pages from the original editions. The official book collection available on the website initially contained only a handful of books: since they could not base themselves on the digitizing efforts of al-Turāth et al., this meant Shamela had to invest a lot of effort in annotating the books in the official collection. The old books from version 2 remained available, but from a separate &lt;a href=&quot;http://shamela.ws/old_site&quot;&gt;page&lt;/a&gt;. It was not until &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20101113112350/http://shamela.ws:80/index.php/page/download-shamela&quot;&gt;November 2010&lt;/a&gt; that the first official collection of Shamela books was launched. It contained 5300 books, almost double the number of books on the old website at the time (2861 books). Simultaneously, a separate &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20101122193841/http://shamela.ws:80/rep.php&quot;&gt;web repository&lt;/a&gt; was launched where books provided by volunteers, and which were not part of the official release, could be stored. This users’ repository currently contains almost 5500 books.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, already in February 2006, an unidentified entity &lt;a href=&quot;https://whois.net/&quot;&gt;registered&lt;/a&gt; the domain name &lt;a href=&quot;https://shamela.ws/&quot;&gt;Shamela.ws&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/.ws&quot;&gt;.ws&lt;/a&gt; is the internet country code for West Samoa, but was popular in the early 2000s because it could be seen as an abbreviation for “Website” or “Webservice” rather than referring to a specific country). Shamela.ws became the official website for al-Maktaba al-Shāmila from &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20070314233042/http://www.shamela.ws:80/&quot;&gt;early 2007&lt;/a&gt; till today, from which the software and the book collection (in its entirety or as separate books) can be downloaded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In those early years, al-Maktaba al-Shāmila was run by a group of volunteers. Their colossal accomplishment did not go unnoticed: Arab and Islamic governments and institutions came under &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alriyadh.com/309892&quot;&gt;criticism&lt;/a&gt; because a group of volunteers had accomplished what they had not been able to do with their multi-billion budgets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.almeshkat.net/book/2287&quot;&gt;2010&lt;/a&gt;, the company “Sharikat al-maktaba al-shāmila li-al-barmajiyyāt” was founded (by Nāfiʿ?) to take sole responsibility of al-Maktaba al-Shāmila and coordinate everything connected to it. The company is based in Egypt, and so is the team responsible for the preparation of the books. Until 2012, it was &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ahlalanbar.net/showthread.php?t=99558&quot;&gt;not supported by any institution&lt;/a&gt;, but depended only on &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20120418162909/http://shamela.ws/index.php/page/how-to-donate&quot;&gt;charitable gifts&lt;/a&gt; from individuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2012, al-Maktaba al-Shāmila came under the patronage/sponsorship (riʿāya) of a Saudi institution, the Daʿwa center in the al-Rawḍa neighbourhood of the Saudi capital Riyad (&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.arrawda.com/&quot;&gt;al-maktab al-taʿāwunī li-al-daʿwa wa-al-irshād wa-tawʿiyyat al-jāliyāt bi-ḥayy al-Ra&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.arrawda.com/&quot;&gt;w&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.arrawda.com/&quot;&gt;ḍa&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, “the cooperative office for propagation and guidance for expatriates in al-Rawḍa district”). Such offices, aimed at spreading Islam, especially among the huge immigrant communities in the kingdom, are present in &lt;a href=&quot;https://d1.islamhouse.com/data/ar/ih_other/ar_Jaliyat_Offices.doc&quot;&gt;many&lt;/a&gt; neighbourhoods in Saudi Arabia. The first effect of this patronage seems to have been a massive influx of funding, allowing a rapid increase of the manpower (literally, all employees &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.arrawdah.com/files/shamela.pdf&quot;&gt;listed&lt;/a&gt; in this period were men). A &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.arrawdah.com/files/shamela.pdf&quot;&gt;pamphlet&lt;/a&gt; on al-Maktaba al-Shāmila, published by al-Rawḍa in 2013 (?), publicizes the growth of the team behind Shamela following the start of its patronage: from one programmer to four (still based in Egypt), and from five data entry employees to thirty. The additional funding was invested in creating new versions of the program to run on iPhone (released in &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20110308061020/http://shamela.ws/index.php/page/epub-for-iphone-and-android&quot;&gt;September 2012&lt;/a&gt;) and Android (released in &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20141006205500/http://shamela.ws/index.php/page/shamela-for-android&quot;&gt;September 2013&lt;/a&gt;) devices, digitizing and correcting new books, and development of additional features for users. The increase in funding was accompanied by a professionalization of the communication department: official Shamela pages were created on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/shamelaofficial&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/Shamela.Official/&quot;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt;, which started publishing news on the library from June 2012 onwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current status of al-Rawḍa’s patronage of Shamela is unclear: a banner proclaiming the support of al-Rawḍa for al-Maktaba al-Shāmila was displayed on the shamela.ws website from &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20120510213030/http://shamela.ws:80/index.php/main&quot;&gt;May&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20120614064312/http://shamela.ws:80/index.php/main&quot;&gt;June 2012&lt;/a&gt; until &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20151020070909/http://shamela.ws:80/index.php/main&quot;&gt;October 2015&lt;/a&gt;, when it was replaced by a banner from another Saudi organization, &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20151109232209/http://www.alrajhiawqaf.org.sa/&quot;&gt;Awqāf al-Rājiḥī&lt;/a&gt; (a private charity set up by the Saudi self-made businessman Ṣāliḥ bin ʿAbd al-ʿAzīz al-Rājiḥī, who died in 2011) until August 2017. The Rawḍa banner re-appeared for a short while (between &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20171120152425/http://shamela.ws:80/index.php/main&quot;&gt;November 2017&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20180507013606/http://shamela.ws:80/index.php/main&quot;&gt;May 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20180507013606/http://shamela.ws:80/index.php/main%5D&quot;&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;) but has since then disappeared, without replacement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have not found direct references to the end of the relationship, but since &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20200306061609/http://www.arrawdah.com:80/dimofinf/&quot;&gt;March&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20200404075525/http://www.arrawdah.com:80/dimofinf/&quot;&gt;2020&lt;/a&gt; the link to al-Maktaba al-Shāmila that featured prominently at the top of al-Rawḍa’s web page has also disappeared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In March 2020, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://shamela.ws/index.php/page/shamela-4&quot;&gt;fourth&lt;/a&gt; version of the software was launched, with a complete overhaul of the database system behind the program (sqlite instead of MS Access) and a new search engine (ElasticSearch). Shamela seemed to have re-invented itself, and well on its way to re-affirm its dominant status among Arabic digital text corpora. However, in the last couple of months, all of Shamela’s official communication channels (Facebook and shamela.ws since May, Twitter since July) have gone silent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NOTE:&lt;/strong&gt; this short history of Shamela was gathered mostly from the archives of the website shamela.ws (long live the &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/&quot;&gt;Internet Archive&lt;/a&gt;!) and the forum Ahlalhdeeth.com (partly &lt;a href=&quot;https://shamela.ws/index.php/search/word/%D8%A3%D8%B1%D8%B4%D9%8A%D9%81+%D9%85%D9%84%D8%AA%D9%82%D9%89+%D8%A3%D9%87%D9%84+%D8%A7%D9%84%D8%AD%D8%AF%D9%8A%D8%AB&quot;&gt;archived&lt;/a&gt; in Shamela). I’d be grateful if readers could point out other sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;shamela-timeline&quot;&gt;Shamela timeline:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ahlalhdeeth.com/vb/showpost.php?p=159996&amp;amp;postcount=90&quot;&gt;2003 (?)&lt;/a&gt;: program created by Nāfiʿ, with 969 books&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20201115224136/https://shamela.ws/index.php/page/about-shamela&quot;&gt;April 2005&lt;/a&gt;: program distributed for free on Ahlalhdeeth forum, under the name &lt;em&gt;al-Mawsūʿa al-Shāmila&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ahlalhdeeth.com/vb/showthread.php?t=30204&quot;&gt;May 2005&lt;/a&gt;: Complaint by al-Turāth, Ahlalhdeeth &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ahlalhdeeth.com/vb//showthread.php?t=30060&quot;&gt;bans&lt;/a&gt; distribution of the program&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20201115224136/https://shamela.ws/index.php/page/about-shamela&quot;&gt;January 2006&lt;/a&gt;: Version 2 (&lt;em&gt;al-Maktaba al-Shāmila al-iṣdār al-thānī&lt;/em&gt;) launched, with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ahlalhdeeth.com/vb/showpost.php?p=577789&amp;amp;postcount=2&quot;&gt;ca. 1800&lt;/a&gt; books&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20060423141146/http://www.islamport.com:80/&quot;&gt;March 2006&lt;/a&gt;: Islamport.com launched as a “search engine with a huge electronic scientific library” with 1800 books from al-Maktaba al-Shāmila and 100 from other sources&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;February 2006: &lt;a href=&quot;https://whois.net/&quot;&gt;registration&lt;/a&gt; of website shamela.ws (will not become active until early 2007)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20070314233042/http://www.shamela.ws:80/&quot;&gt;March 2007&lt;/a&gt;: Shamela.ws becomes the official website of al-Maktaba al-Shāmila, coinciding with an update of the program to version 2.11.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20201115224136/https://shamela.ws/index.php/page/about-shamela&quot;&gt;June 2008&lt;/a&gt;: Shamela Version 3 launched: with small collection of books with official Shamela stamp&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20101113112350/http://shamela.ws:80/index.php/page/download-shamela&quot;&gt;November 2010&lt;/a&gt;: First release of the official collection of Shamela books (5300 books), and of a separate &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20101122193841/http://shamela.ws:80/rep.php&quot;&gt;web repository&lt;/a&gt; where books uploaded by members could be stored.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20120312190125/http://shamela.ws/browse.php&quot;&gt;March 2012&lt;/a&gt;: launch of the online browsable version of the official collection&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20120614064312/http://shamela.ws/index.php/main&quot;&gt;June 2012&lt;/a&gt;: Second release of the official collection of Shamela books (6111 books)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20130629092649/http://shamela.ws/index.php/page/shamela-for-ios&quot;&gt;September 2012&lt;/a&gt;: launch of Shamela for iPhone and iPad&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20141006205500/http://shamela.ws/index.php/page/shamela-for-android&quot;&gt;September 2013&lt;/a&gt;: launch of Shamela for Android&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;October 2015 – August 2017: Shamela sponsored by &lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20151109232209/http://www.alrajhiawqaf.org.sa/&quot;&gt;Awqāf Muḥammad ʿAbd al-ʿAzīz al-Rajḥī&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20151222035645/http://shamela.ws:80/index.php/page/download-shamela&quot;&gt;December 2015&lt;/a&gt;: Technical development of version 3 halted (v. 3.64)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20170812235857/http://al-maktaba.org/&quot;&gt;August 2017&lt;/a&gt;: launch of al-maktaba.org, which presents itself as “the modern al-Maktaba al-Shāmila” (but is unrelated) and offers an updated browse and search interface to al-Maktaba al-Shāmila&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;May 2019: last books added to the official collection of al-Maktaba al-Shamela&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://web.archive.org/web/20200424160128/http://shamela.ws:80/index.php/page/download-shamela&quot;&gt;April 2020&lt;/a&gt;: Shamela version 4 launched, with ca. 7000 books.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Peter Verkinderen</name></author><summary type="html">(This is the first blog post in a longer series of posts about the sources of OpenITI) Al-Maktaba al-Shāmila (“The comprehensive library”, often referred to simply as Shamela) is a free software that aims at providing a digital research environment for Islamic scholars, and comes with a large collection of Arabic primary sources and secondary texts. It has millions of users in the Islamic world, and is also widely used in academia. It is currently the largest source of texts in the OpenITI corpus: about 45% of the texts in the corpus come from Shamela. In its first iteration, it was called al-mawsūʿa al-shāmila (“The Comprehensive Encyclopaedia”). The program was created by an Egyptian member of the Ahl al-Ḥadīth forum known only as Nāfiʿ (often referred to affectionately on specialized internet fora as al-akh Nāfiʿ  “Brother Nāfiʿ” or duktūr / al-ustādh Nāfiʿ “Dr. Nāfiʿ”). When the program, containing 969 free books, first appeared on internet fora for Islamic scholars in early 2005, it met with a lot of enthusiasm. So much so that the pioneering publishing house of digital texts, Markaz al-Turāth lil-barāmijāt (the publisher of al-Jāmiʿ al-Kabīr, that other main source of texts in our corpus), launched an acrimonious attack against the program on the Ahl al-Ḥadīth forum, accusing Nāfiʿ of stealing its software and content. This post led to such a heated discussion that the forum moderators had to remove the thread, and ban all content related to al-mawsūʿa al-shāmila on 4 May 2005. A new discussion thread was eventually opened on 7 May, with a statement from al-Turāth and a response from the forum moderators. In its statement, al-Turāth apologized for their earlier reaction, before explaining in detail why it considered the program an act of theft (of digitized texts and specialized data) that would kill off not only the company but also all industry-led digitization efforts. In their reaction, the forum moderators thanked al-Turāth for their huge service to the field and Islām, but also defended its forum members involved in the creation and distribution of the program as driven only by love for Islam. The discussion lasted for weeks, and eventually prompted Nāfiʿ, the creator of the program himself, to react in a post on the forum. In his statement, he claimed he had developed the program for himself, to enable him to simultaneously search the different collections of digital books all of which he had legally. While admitting these included books from al-Turāth, he strenuously denied that Shamela was “al-Turāth in another jacket”, adducing proof that he had included books and data from many different sources. He claimed not to have shared his program with more than a handful of scholars, and to have been surprised when he noticed, two years later, another member of the Ahl al-Ḥadīth forum, with whom he had not shared the program, and whom he did not even know, offering it (for free) to other members. He also vowed to create a new version of the program that did not include any book taken from a commercial product. After seemingly conciliatory rhetoric from both sides, the discussion turned bitter again, resulting in repeated accusations of piracy and calls for a boycott flying in both directions. In January 2006 Nāfiʿ finally published the promised second version (al-iṣdār al-thānī) of the program, under the title al-Maktaba al-Shāmila (“The Comprehensive Library”). As he had vowed, it did not include material taken (directly) from al-Turāth products, but only from free websites and internet fora. This meant that it could not offer a number of important features of the first version: the page numbers of most texts did not agree with any published edition, and services like identification of ḥadīth transmitters and historical figures, which had been based on databases from al-Turāth, were absent. On the flip side, the program was still free, and contained a much larger number of texts than the first version, ca. 1800 books. In addition to a greatly increased collection of digitized books, the most important feature of the second version was that it was the first program of its kind that offered the user the possibility to import their own texts into the program so they could create their own personal library. At the same time, this opened the door for people to keep using the program for reading and searching texts from companies like al-Turāth, without Shamela having to take responsibility for this. Shamela was the first program of its kind to offer this kind of feature, and it probably played an important role in its great success. Using this feature, a number of groups and individuals started publishing their own versions of al-Maktaba al-Shāmila with many additional texts (e.g., the augmented Shamela collection of Islamport.com contained already 3.300 books in September 2006 and more than 5.000 books in March 2007; al-Maktaba al-Shāmila al-Dhahabiyya contained 29.000 books in 2019). A number of these apocryphal shamela collections were created by groups from a minority (non-Sunnī) Islamic community (e.g., al-Maktaba al-Zaydiyya al-Shāmila, al-Maktaba al-Shāmila al-Ibāḍiyya), whose books were not represented in the main Shamela collection. We will discuss these unofficial shamela collections in a later blog. At first, Shamela Version 2 was distributed via internet fora, as was the first version: due to limited stable internet access and bandwidth in much of the world at that time. The book collection was downloadable from a variety of internet fora and file sharing websites (including the then very recent website waqfeya.net); and users were encouraged to share copies of the program on CDs with people who did not have stable internet access. The third version, released on 3 June 2008, represented an audacious step: Shamela decided to create a dedicated collection of books of its own that recreated the features lost in the second version after the dispute with al-Turāth. Books from this official Shamela collection would have page numbers that agreed with the printed editions, and would enable special features like a takhrīj function for ḥadīth works (which would identify the sources for a ḥadīth). However, the user would still be able to use the program for both the official collection and external books (using an improved import mechanism). An additional well-received feature was that both official and external books could be linked to scanned pages from the original editions. The official book collection available on the website initially contained only a handful of books: since they could not base themselves on the digitizing efforts of al-Turāth et al., this meant Shamela had to invest a lot of effort in annotating the books in the official collection. The old books from version 2 remained available, but from a separate page. It was not until November 2010 that the first official collection of Shamela books was launched. It contained 5300 books, almost double the number of books on the old website at the time (2861 books). Simultaneously, a separate web repository was launched where books provided by volunteers, and which were not part of the official release, could be stored. This users’ repository currently contains almost 5500 books. However, already in February 2006, an unidentified entity registered the domain name Shamela.ws (.ws is the internet country code for West Samoa, but was popular in the early 2000s because it could be seen as an abbreviation for “Website” or “Webservice” rather than referring to a specific country). Shamela.ws became the official website for al-Maktaba al-Shāmila from early 2007 till today, from which the software and the book collection (in its entirety or as separate books) can be downloaded. In those early years, al-Maktaba al-Shāmila was run by a group of volunteers. Their colossal accomplishment did not go unnoticed: Arab and Islamic governments and institutions came under criticism because a group of volunteers had accomplished what they had not been able to do with their multi-billion budgets. In 2010, the company “Sharikat al-maktaba al-shāmila li-al-barmajiyyāt” was founded (by Nāfiʿ?) to take sole responsibility of al-Maktaba al-Shāmila and coordinate everything connected to it. The company is based in Egypt, and so is the team responsible for the preparation of the books. Until 2012, it was not supported by any institution, but depended only on charitable gifts from individuals. In 2012, al-Maktaba al-Shāmila came under the patronage/sponsorship (riʿāya) of a Saudi institution, the Daʿwa center in the al-Rawḍa neighbourhood of the Saudi capital Riyad (al-maktab al-taʿāwunī li-al-daʿwa wa-al-irshād wa-tawʿiyyat al-jāliyāt bi-ḥayy al-Rawḍa, “the cooperative office for propagation and guidance for expatriates in al-Rawḍa district”). Such offices, aimed at spreading Islam, especially among the huge immigrant communities in the kingdom, are present in many neighbourhoods in Saudi Arabia. The first effect of this patronage seems to have been a massive influx of funding, allowing a rapid increase of the manpower (literally, all employees listed in this period were men). A pamphlet on al-Maktaba al-Shāmila, published by al-Rawḍa in 2013 (?), publicizes the growth of the team behind Shamela following the start of its patronage: from one programmer to four (still based in Egypt), and from five data entry employees to thirty. The additional funding was invested in creating new versions of the program to run on iPhone (released in September 2012) and Android (released in September 2013) devices, digitizing and correcting new books, and development of additional features for users. The increase in funding was accompanied by a professionalization of the communication department: official Shamela pages were created on Twitter and Facebook, which started publishing news on the library from June 2012 onwards. The current status of al-Rawḍa’s patronage of Shamela is unclear: a banner proclaiming the support of al-Rawḍa for al-Maktaba al-Shāmila was displayed on the shamela.ws website from May / June 2012 until October 2015, when it was replaced by a banner from another Saudi organization, Awqāf al-Rājiḥī (a private charity set up by the Saudi self-made businessman Ṣāliḥ bin ʿAbd al-ʿAzīz al-Rājiḥī, who died in 2011) until August 2017. The Rawḍa banner re-appeared for a short while (between November 2017 and May 2018)) but has since then disappeared, without replacement. I have not found direct references to the end of the relationship, but since March 2020 the link to al-Maktaba al-Shāmila that featured prominently at the top of al-Rawḍa’s web page has also disappeared. In March 2020, the fourth version of the software was launched, with a complete overhaul of the database system behind the program (sqlite instead of MS Access) and a new search engine (ElasticSearch). Shamela seemed to have re-invented itself, and well on its way to re-affirm its dominant status among Arabic digital text corpora. However, in the last couple of months, all of Shamela’s official communication channels (Facebook and shamela.ws since May, Twitter since July) have gone silent. NOTE: this short history of Shamela was gathered mostly from the archives of the website shamela.ws (long live the Internet Archive!) and the forum Ahlalhdeeth.com (partly archived in Shamela). I’d be grateful if readers could point out other sources. Shamela timeline: 2003 (?): program created by Nāfiʿ, with 969 books April 2005: program distributed for free on Ahlalhdeeth forum, under the name al-Mawsūʿa al-Shāmila May 2005: Complaint by al-Turāth, Ahlalhdeeth bans distribution of the program January 2006: Version 2 (al-Maktaba al-Shāmila al-iṣdār al-thānī) launched, with ca. 1800 books March 2006: Islamport.com launched as a “search engine with a huge electronic scientific library” with 1800 books from al-Maktaba al-Shāmila and 100 from other sources February 2006: registration of website shamela.ws (will not become active until early 2007) March 2007: Shamela.ws becomes the official website of al-Maktaba al-Shāmila, coinciding with an update of the program to version 2.11. June 2008: Shamela Version 3 launched: with small collection of books with official Shamela stamp November 2010: First release of the official collection of Shamela books (5300 books), and of a separate web repository where books uploaded by members could be stored. March 2012: launch of the online browsable version of the official collection June 2012: Second release of the official collection of Shamela books (6111 books) September 2012: launch of Shamela for iPhone and iPad September 2013: launch of Shamela for Android October 2015 – August 2017: Shamela sponsored by Awqāf Muḥammad ʿAbd al-ʿAzīz al-Rajḥī December 2015: Technical development of version 3 halted (v. 3.64) August 2017: launch of al-maktaba.org, which presents itself as “the modern al-Maktaba al-Shāmila” (but is unrelated) and offers an updated browse and search interface to al-Maktaba al-Shāmila May 2019: last books added to the official collection of al-Maktaba al-Shamela April 2020: Shamela version 4 launched, with ca. 7000 books.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">KITAB postdoc Gowaart Van Den Bossche wins BRAIS-De Gruyter dissertation prize – 2020</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11-19.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="KITAB postdoc Gowaart Van Den Bossche wins BRAIS-De Gruyter dissertation prize – 2020" /><published>2020-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/KITAB%20postdoc%20Gowaart%20Van%20Den%20Bossche%20wins%20BRAIS-De%20Gruyter%20dissertation%20prize%20%E2%80%93%202020</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11-19.html">&lt;p&gt;The British Association for Islamic Studies (BRAIS) and De Gruyter have announced the outcome of the fifth (2020) round of the BRAIS – De Gruyter Prize in the Study of Islam and the Muslim World. The winning submission is Gowaart Van Den Bossche’s PhD thesis, which he defended in 2019 at Ghent University, right before joining the KITAB project as a postdoctoral fellow. In his own words:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’m very happy with this recognition of my PhD work. It’s especially nice to see this kind of historical research appreciated by an organisation that does not limit itself to my field of study (Mamluk studies, or even Islamic history) but tries to connect people across Islamic studies. In a way that resonates nicely with ISMC’s own mission.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gowaart will be turning his dissertation into a monograph and enrich it by including data from his ongoing work in the KITAB project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/old_posts/BRAIS3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Anjum Alam</name></author><summary type="html">The British Association for Islamic Studies (BRAIS) and De Gruyter have announced the outcome of the fifth (2020) round of the BRAIS – De Gruyter Prize in the Study of Islam and the Muslim World. The winning submission is Gowaart Van Den Bossche’s PhD thesis, which he defended in 2019 at Ghent University, right before joining the KITAB project as a postdoctoral fellow. In his own words: “I’m very happy with this recognition of my PhD work. It’s especially nice to see this kind of historical research appreciated by an organisation that does not limit itself to my field of study (Mamluk studies, or even Islamic history) but tries to connect people across Islamic studies. In a way that resonates nicely with ISMC’s own mission.” Gowaart will be turning his dissertation into a monograph and enrich it by including data from his ongoing work in the KITAB project.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">OpenITI release 2020.2.3</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/10-19.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="OpenITI release 2020.2.3" /><published>2020-10-19T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-10-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/OpenITI%20release%202020.2.3</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/10-19.html">&lt;p&gt;A new version (version 2020.2.3) of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenITI&quot;&gt;OpenITI&lt;/a&gt; corpus is available at &lt;a href=&quot;https://zenodo.org/record/4075046&quot;&gt;Zenodo&lt;/a&gt;, an Open Science platform that supports Open Access. This is the third release (second release in 2020) developed by the OpenITI organization. It is also accessible at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenITI/RELEASE&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current release features 7,725 books, including all versions and editions (1,573,262,381 words), of which 4,781 are unique books written by 2,074  authors. In the release, 680 new books (with their ids) have been added. In terms of annotation, 773 books are available in first-stage OpenITI mARkdown, of which 79 have been reviewed and vetted by the annotation team (this being the second stage of our annotation process). The vetted texts have .mARkdown extension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new texts and changes to the URIs as well as the statistics on the corpus are listed in the release note, which is available in the publication link above (also available &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/OpenITI/RELEASE/blob/master/OpenITI_release-note_2020-2-3.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are adding more texts to the OpenITI corpus. If you wish to contribute to OpenITI and add books or manuscripts that are not in the OpenITI please contact Lorenz Nigst or any of the team members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To cite this version please use the following manner. The bibliographical export is also available at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://zenodo.org/record/3891466&quot;&gt;publication page&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lorenz  Nigst, Maxim Romanov, Sarah Bowen Savant, Masoumeh Seydi, &amp;amp; Peter Verkinderen. (2020). OpenITI: a Machine-Readable Corpus of Islamicate Texts (Version 2020.2.3) [Data set]. Zenodo. http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4075046&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Masoumeh Seydi</name></author><summary type="html">A new version (version 2020.2.3) of the OpenITI corpus is available at Zenodo, an Open Science platform that supports Open Access. This is the third release (second release in 2020) developed by the OpenITI organization. It is also accessible at GitHub. The current release features 7,725 books, including all versions and editions (1,573,262,381 words), of which 4,781 are unique books written by 2,074  authors. In the release, 680 new books (with their ids) have been added. In terms of annotation, 773 books are available in first-stage OpenITI mARkdown, of which 79 have been reviewed and vetted by the annotation team (this being the second stage of our annotation process). The vetted texts have .mARkdown extension. The new texts and changes to the URIs as well as the statistics on the corpus are listed in the release note, which is available in the publication link above (also available here). We are adding more texts to the OpenITI corpus. If you wish to contribute to OpenITI and add books or manuscripts that are not in the OpenITI please contact Lorenz Nigst or any of the team members. To cite this version please use the following manner. The bibliographical export is also available at the publication page: Lorenz  Nigst, Maxim Romanov, Sarah Bowen Savant, Masoumeh Seydi, &amp;amp; Peter Verkinderen. (2020). OpenITI: a Machine-Readable Corpus of Islamicate Texts (Version 2020.2.3) [Data set]. Zenodo. http://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4075046</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mapping Who’s Who in Isnads – First Steps</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/10-05.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mapping Who’s Who in Isnads – First Steps" /><published>2020-10-05T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-10-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/Mapping%20Who%E2%80%99s%20Who%20in%20Isnads%20%E2%80%93%20First%20Steps</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/10-05.html">&lt;p&gt;One of the major challenges for those working with historical Arabic texts is the names, and the variety of ways that authors might refer to the same person. An author might, for example, refer to someone as ‘Hisham’, or as ‘the father of ʿUmar’, or as ‘the son of ʿAbbas’. These names might also be joined up when an author quotes ‘Hisham, the father of ʿUmar’, or when he writes about ‘the father of ʿUmar, Hisham’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Identifying the person in question matters for many reasons. To name but a few: We want to make texts in the OpenITI corpus searchable, and need to be able to pinpoint persons, whatever variation of the name is used (and also to distinguish between the different Hishams). For studying transmission and book history, we also want to know who’s who. &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/02-03.html&quot;&gt;Ryan Muther&lt;/a&gt; is working on a method that automatically locates &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s within texts. Who are these people? Likewise, we have much data aligning later works with earlier sources. We want to be able to read citations. Who precisely is being cited?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We (Sarah Savant and Masoumeh Seydi) have been working on a way to link people to varieties of names and chose as a case study the &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh Madinat Dimashq&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;TMD&lt;/em&gt;) by Ibn ʿAsakir (d. 571/1176).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It is one of the largest works in the OpenITI corpus, with 80 volumes in the Dar al-Fikr printed edition, and a word count of over 8 million. It consists of a first volume, treating the history of the city, including its ancient roots and seventh–century conquest and a second volume, treating the topography of the city. The remainder of the book comprises biographies of the elites who lived or passed through Damascus prior to Ibn ʿAsakir’s time. Based on Muther’s data, 39% of this massive work is made up of &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s, which is more than 3 million words worth of &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s. To put it mildly, that is a lot of names, and each is typically written in a variety of ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our text reuse data suggests that Ibn ʿAsakir, in creating his mammoth work, relied heavily upon earlier books, including the &lt;em&gt;Kitab al-Tabaqat al-kabir&lt;/em&gt; of Ibn Saʿd (d. 235/830). We wanted to specifically see if we could work out the route – or routes – through which Ibn ʿAsakir accessed the &lt;em&gt;Tabaqat&lt;/em&gt;. Did he have access to this book through a specific transmission line, as has been recently argued by specialists of Ibn ʿAsakir?&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-method&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Method&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using a search pattern called ‘regular expressions’, we collected all transmission chains within the &lt;em&gt;TMD&lt;/em&gt; that included Ibn Saʿd.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:3&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; We then trimmed the chains to include only names spanning between Ibn Saʿd and Ibn ʿAsakir. Relying on a transmissive term list prepared by Kevin Jaques, plus some editing, we removed non-name material. To deal with the variant ways of referring to the same person, we created an authorities list to map variations. The authorities list relied on a Latin-script name to unify variant Arabic-script names in the &lt;em&gt;TMD isnad&lt;/em&gt;s, as exemplified below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Ibn Hayyawayh&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;أبو عمر بن حيوية&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Ibn Hayyawayh&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;أبي عمر بن حيويه&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Ibn Hayyawayh&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;أبو عمر ابن حيوية&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Ibn Hayyawayh&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;أبو عمر محمد بن العباس بن حيوية&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Ibn Hayyawayh&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;أبو عمر محمد ابن العباس&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Ibn Hayyawayh&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;أبي عمر محمد بن العباس بن حيوية&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Ibn Hayyawayh&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;ابن عباس&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Ibn Hayyawayh&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;محمد بن العباس&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Ibn Hayyawayh&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;محمد ابن العباس&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Ibn Hayyawayh&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;محمد بن العباس بن حيويه الخزاز&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Ibn Hayyawayh&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;أبو عمر محمد بن العباس&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Ibn Hayyawayh&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;محمد بن العباس لخزاز&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Table 1&lt;/strong&gt;: Reconciling variations of names within &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s that feature Muḥammad b. Saʿd. The name of Abu ʿUmar b. Ḥayyawayh (d. 373/983-84) is written in many ways representing differences in orthography and name elements (e.g., whether a &lt;em&gt;kunya&lt;/em&gt; such as ‘father of so-and-so’ is used). The data file from which this list is excerpted contains 427 such equations for names in Ibn Saʿd &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Masoumeh Seydi then used the Levenshtein distance algorithm to group together the most similar chains of names. Even with the reduction of the name variants to single versions, the data remained too extensive to see patterns. So, we filtered the total data set to look for only the most commonly occurring transmissive chains, and only those with 6 nodes, by far the most commonly occurring length.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:4&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/old_posts/table-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Table 2&lt;/strong&gt;: The most frequently occurring six-person &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s that run back to Muhammad b. Saʾd. Pruning the data to get these transmissive lines involved excluding 217 lines of other six-person &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seydi then graphed the dramatically filtered data, which produced the following graph.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/old_posts/Image3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Graph 1&lt;/strong&gt;: This graph represents the small subset of lines of transmission running back to Ibn Saʿd in the table above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The graph features one coherent chain – in red – that runs back to Ibn Saʿd via Abu Bakr Muhammad b. Shujaʿ (d. 533/1138), Abu ʿAmr b. Manda (d. 475/1082-83), Abu Muhammad b. Yawh (n.d.), Ahmad b. Muhammad al-Lanbani (n.d.), and Ibn Abi Dunya (d. 281/894). The other chains, in the left part of the graph, involve 9 transmitters in the five generations prior to Ibn Saʿd. The transmissive lines cross one another and appear something like a map of the London underground. A key goal in designing the graph was to distinguish the actual transmission lines, whereas graphs of &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s might fail to distinguish potential from actual paths. A next step would be weighting the lines for how often they occur in our dataset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The effort required to create this data set is important. The &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s were not sitting there ready to be plucked from the &lt;em&gt;TMD&lt;/em&gt;, but required many hours of painstaking disambiguation of names and pruning of data. We leave much on the cutting room floor, and the left of the graph does not yield a simple picture of transmission. This messiness suggests the vagaries of naming practices, and the deterioration of information through the transmission process. But it also suggests that the way that Ibn ʿAsakir accessed the wisdom of earlier centuries was likely quite complex. Different parts of Ibn Saʿd’s oeuvre may have passed through different of these lines. Or, the transmission may have been more mediated than that, with Ibn ʿAsakir accessing a more dispersed corpus of Ibn Saʿd materials. He may even have been judging the relative merits of different tradents for different pieces of information. It is hard to know whether his audience could track the varieties of names or the contents that mapped to lines (perhaps not), but the sheer number of them was part of their expectations of a book such as his.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:5&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Giving them what they expected, Ibn ʿAsakir performed his role as a major scholar in the post-canonical era of Hadith transmission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;just-the-start&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Just the Start&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tracking these persons is just the start of understanding how Ibn ʿAsakir accessed transmissions from Ibn Saʿd. But three points are already evident and point the way for further areas of exploration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ibn ʿAsakir cites people for his knowledge from Ibn Saʿd, whereas he does not generally choose to cite a book. The choice to cite people rather than books reflects the knowledge environment in which Ibn ʿAsakir worked. The title &lt;em&gt;al-Tabaqat al-kabir&lt;/em&gt; occurs in only two spots in the &lt;em&gt;TMD&lt;/em&gt;, and once in direct proximity to a transmissive chain. The title &lt;em&gt;al-Tabaqat al-saghir&lt;/em&gt; occurs twice, outside of an &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt; (the relationship between the two &lt;em&gt;Tabaqat&lt;/em&gt; works is a subject of some scholarly discussion). The simpler title, &lt;em&gt;al-Tabaqat&lt;/em&gt;, is also attributed to Ibn ʿAsakir a handful of times (though more often to other authors who wrote such works). Meaning, that the vast number of times that Ibn ʿAsakir mentions Ibn Saʿd, he does so without direct reference to a work. This matters for both how Ibn ʿAsakir was working and for what he wanted his audience to know.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The choice to cite people rather than books notwithstanding, the &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s in Table 2 might be helpful for understanding the transmission history of Ibn Saʿd’s book. Scholars today commonly refer to recensions by al-Husayn b. Fahm (d. 289/902), al-Harith b. Abi Usama (d. 282/895), and possibly, Ibn Abi ’l-Dunya (though the latter perhaps only for &lt;em&gt;al-Tabaqat al-saghir&lt;/em&gt;, as argued by Jens Scheiner).&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:6&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The roles of the other tradents in Table 2 and Graph 1 need exploring. In particular, the parts played by Abu Muhammad al-Jawhari (d. 454/1062), Abu Ishaq al-Barmaki (d. 445/1053), Abu Bakr Muhammad b. ʿAbd al-Baqi (d. 535/1140), and Abu Ghalib (d. 527/1132) might be studied by collecting their transmissions from Ibn Saʿd to see whether contents within them might represent distinct pieces of the &lt;em&gt;Tabaqat al-kabir&lt;/em&gt;. Do citations from a particular chain always come from the same part of Ibn Saʿd’s work? Are Ibn Saʿd citations possibly pulled from the sort of hadith booklets studied by Konrad Hirschler? As Jaques has argued for Ibn Ishaq’s (d. 151/767) &lt;em&gt;Sira&lt;/em&gt;, we should also keep our minds open to the possibility that there was not one &lt;em&gt;al-Tabaqat al-kabir&lt;/em&gt;, but possibly different versions produced by Ibn Saʿd himself.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The citations of Ibn Saʿd, within the &lt;em&gt;TMD&lt;/em&gt;, do not map easily to the reuse alignments we generate independently with &lt;a href=&quot;/about-passim/&quot;&gt;passim&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:7&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Why this might be the case is complicated, but seems to arise ultimately (and mostly) from a) the fact that Ibn ʿAsakir is working with various transmissions from Ibn Saʿd, and these might have been passed on in pieces through written notebooks or collations, as just mentioned (meaning, the transmission &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; highly mediated); b) the alignment data we have is based on a specific edition of &lt;a href=&quot;http://0230ibnsacd.tabaqatkubra.shamela0001686-ara1/&quot;&gt;Ibn Saʿd’s text&lt;/a&gt; held in the OpenITI. In other cases, when an author relied directly upon an earlier work, citations map much more easily to text reuse alignments.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These points suggest that we should be exploring the way that Ibn ʿAsakir cites his information more generally (including the role of transmission from people versus books) and the extent to which distinct transmission chains that include authors of well-known and surviving works might belong to distinct pieces of their books. Does he have at hand books themselves, even if he does not typically cite them directly?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our lines of enquiry will help us to understand both the reception of Ibn Saʿd’s book, and also how an author such as Ibn ʿAsakir, in producing his massive book, went about his work. Before we can get started, though, we need to work on the names that feature in citations, and that is why named entity recognition, and the ability to cluster related chains of transmission, are so important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For computer scientists, this sort of work is part of a new stock-in-trade of the digital humanities. For historians, it takes time and patience and iteration. Creating lists of name variants is frankly best done with music running in the background and plans for an evening outside. Working on manuscripts, scholars develop skills, including the ability to read and differentiate different scripts. Patience is required. For understanding books in their digital format, named entity recognition might just be a parallel to this sort of work, with rewards aplenty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;notes&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The OpenITI file that we used for this chapter, 0571IbnCasakir.TarikhDimashq.JK000916-ara1, is based on the 80-volume, 1995-2001 Dar al-Fikr edition edited by ʿUmar al-ʿAmrawi and ʿAli Shiri, but excludes volumes 71-80. Volumes 71-74 represent a &lt;em&gt;mustadrak&lt;/em&gt;, or amendment by the editors (including additional biographical entries); these volumes have now been added to the OpenITI file based on another file in the OpenITI containing the entire Dar al-Fikr work (0571IbnCasakir.TarikhDimashq.Shamela000071-ara1, containing 8.5 million words). Volumes 75-80 represent indices (not added). Gowaart Van Den Bossche and Hamid Reza Hakimi annotated the file for the KITAB project. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;See e.g., Jens Scheiner,  ‘Ibn ʿAsakir’s Virtual Library as Reflected in His &lt;em&gt;TMD&lt;/em&gt;,’ in &lt;em&gt;New Perspectives on Ibn ʿAsakir in Islamic Historiography&lt;/em&gt;, ed. Steven Judd and Scheiner (Leiden: Brill, 2017), pp. 156-257, esp. at pp. 179-82. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:3&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;‘Regular expressions’ is the name of a formalized way of constructing search patterns, implemented in many computer languages and much text editing software. Regular expressions can be used, for example, to allow for intervening words or to locate passages that cross pages or other boundaries. See Jan Goyvaerts and Steven Levithan, &lt;em&gt;Regular Expressions Cookbook&lt;/em&gt;, 2nd. rev. ed. (Farnham: O’Reilly, 2012). &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:3&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:4&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;There were also &lt;em&gt;isnad&lt;/em&gt;s with between 7 and 12 transmitters within them, but 6 nodes was by far the most common. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:4&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:5&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For reflections on varieties of names in another context, and challenges of pinning names to titles, see Konrad Hirschler, &lt;em&gt;A Monument to Medieval Syrian Book Culture: The Library of Ibn ʻAbd al-Hadi&lt;/em&gt; (Edinburgh: Edinburgh University Press, 2020), pp. 177-78. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:5&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:6&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Scheiner, ‘Ibn ʿAsakir’s Virtual Library,’ p. 181-82 and p. 269. I use death dates for tradents from Scheiner and from Ahmad Nazir Atassi, ‘The transmission of Ibn Saʿd’s biographical dictionary &lt;em&gt;Kitab al-tabaqāt al-kabir&lt;/em&gt;,’ &lt;em&gt;Journal of Arabic and Islamic Studies&lt;/em&gt;(2012), pp. 56–80. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:6&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:7&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Atassi has noted that ‘expecting a verbatim match between the reports found in a consulted compilation and the corresponding report in the printed [&lt;em&gt;al-Tabaqat al-kabir&lt;/em&gt;] is unrealistic.’ ‘The transmission of Ibn Saʿd’s biographical dictionary,’ p. 73. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:7&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Sarah Savant and Masoumeh Seydi</name></author><summary type="html">One of the major challenges for those working with historical Arabic texts is the names, and the variety of ways that authors might refer to the same person. An author might, for example, refer to someone as ‘Hisham’, or as ‘the father of ʿUmar’, or as ‘the son of ʿAbbas’. These names might also be joined up when an author quotes ‘Hisham, the father of ʿUmar’, or when he writes about ‘the father of ʿUmar, Hisham’. Identifying the person in question matters for many reasons. To name but a few: We want to make texts in the OpenITI corpus searchable, and need to be able to pinpoint persons, whatever variation of the name is used (and also to distinguish between the different Hishams). For studying transmission and book history, we also want to know who’s who. Ryan Muther is working on a method that automatically locates isnads within texts. Who are these people? Likewise, we have much data aligning later works with earlier sources. We want to be able to read citations. Who precisely is being cited? We (Sarah Savant and Masoumeh Seydi) have been working on a way to link people to varieties of names and chose as a case study the Taʾrikh Madinat Dimashq (TMD) by Ibn ʿAsakir (d. 571/1176).1 It is one of the largest works in the OpenITI corpus, with 80 volumes in the Dar al-Fikr printed edition, and a word count of over 8 million. It consists of a first volume, treating the history of the city, including its ancient roots and seventh–century conquest and a second volume, treating the topography of the city. The remainder of the book comprises biographies of the elites who lived or passed through Damascus prior to Ibn ʿAsakir’s time. Based on Muther’s data, 39% of this massive work is made up of isnads, which is more than 3 million words worth of isnads. To put it mildly, that is a lot of names, and each is typically written in a variety of ways. Our text reuse data suggests that Ibn ʿAsakir, in creating his mammoth work, relied heavily upon earlier books, including the Kitab al-Tabaqat al-kabir of Ibn Saʿd (d. 235/830). We wanted to specifically see if we could work out the route – or routes – through which Ibn ʿAsakir accessed the Tabaqat. Did he have access to this book through a specific transmission line, as has been recently argued by specialists of Ibn ʿAsakir?2 The Method Using a search pattern called ‘regular expressions’, we collected all transmission chains within the TMD that included Ibn Saʿd.3 We then trimmed the chains to include only names spanning between Ibn Saʿd and Ibn ʿAsakir. Relying on a transmissive term list prepared by Kevin Jaques, plus some editing, we removed non-name material. To deal with the variant ways of referring to the same person, we created an authorities list to map variations. The authorities list relied on a Latin-script name to unify variant Arabic-script names in the TMD isnads, as exemplified below: Ibn Hayyawayh أبو عمر بن حيوية Ibn Hayyawayh أبي عمر بن حيويه Ibn Hayyawayh أبو عمر ابن حيوية Ibn Hayyawayh أبو عمر محمد بن العباس بن حيوية Ibn Hayyawayh أبو عمر محمد ابن العباس Ibn Hayyawayh أبي عمر محمد بن العباس بن حيوية Ibn Hayyawayh ابن عباس Ibn Hayyawayh محمد بن العباس Ibn Hayyawayh محمد ابن العباس Ibn Hayyawayh محمد بن العباس بن حيويه الخزاز Ibn Hayyawayh أبو عمر محمد بن العباس Ibn Hayyawayh محمد بن العباس لخزاز Table 1: Reconciling variations of names within isnads that feature Muḥammad b. Saʿd. The name of Abu ʿUmar b. Ḥayyawayh (d. 373/983-84) is written in many ways representing differences in orthography and name elements (e.g., whether a kunya such as ‘father of so-and-so’ is used). The data file from which this list is excerpted contains 427 such equations for names in Ibn Saʿd isnads. Masoumeh Seydi then used the Levenshtein distance algorithm to group together the most similar chains of names. Even with the reduction of the name variants to single versions, the data remained too extensive to see patterns. So, we filtered the total data set to look for only the most commonly occurring transmissive chains, and only those with 6 nodes, by far the most commonly occurring length.4 Table 2: The most frequently occurring six-person isnads that run back to Muhammad b. Saʾd. Pruning the data to get these transmissive lines involved excluding 217 lines of other six-person isnads. Seydi then graphed the dramatically filtered data, which produced the following graph. Graph 1: This graph represents the small subset of lines of transmission running back to Ibn Saʿd in the table above. The graph features one coherent chain – in red – that runs back to Ibn Saʿd via Abu Bakr Muhammad b. Shujaʿ (d. 533/1138), Abu ʿAmr b. Manda (d. 475/1082-83), Abu Muhammad b. Yawh (n.d.), Ahmad b. Muhammad al-Lanbani (n.d.), and Ibn Abi Dunya (d. 281/894). The other chains, in the left part of the graph, involve 9 transmitters in the five generations prior to Ibn Saʿd. The transmissive lines cross one another and appear something like a map of the London underground. A key goal in designing the graph was to distinguish the actual transmission lines, whereas graphs of isnads might fail to distinguish potential from actual paths. A next step would be weighting the lines for how often they occur in our dataset. The effort required to create this data set is important. The isnads were not sitting there ready to be plucked from the TMD, but required many hours of painstaking disambiguation of names and pruning of data. We leave much on the cutting room floor, and the left of the graph does not yield a simple picture of transmission. This messiness suggests the vagaries of naming practices, and the deterioration of information through the transmission process. But it also suggests that the way that Ibn ʿAsakir accessed the wisdom of earlier centuries was likely quite complex. Different parts of Ibn Saʿd’s oeuvre may have passed through different of these lines. Or, the transmission may have been more mediated than that, with Ibn ʿAsakir accessing a more dispersed corpus of Ibn Saʿd materials. He may even have been judging the relative merits of different tradents for different pieces of information. It is hard to know whether his audience could track the varieties of names or the contents that mapped to lines (perhaps not), but the sheer number of them was part of their expectations of a book such as his.5 Giving them what they expected, Ibn ʿAsakir performed his role as a major scholar in the post-canonical era of Hadith transmission. Just the Start Tracking these persons is just the start of understanding how Ibn ʿAsakir accessed transmissions from Ibn Saʿd. But three points are already evident and point the way for further areas of exploration. Ibn ʿAsakir cites people for his knowledge from Ibn Saʿd, whereas he does not generally choose to cite a book. The choice to cite people rather than books reflects the knowledge environment in which Ibn ʿAsakir worked. The title al-Tabaqat al-kabir occurs in only two spots in the TMD, and once in direct proximity to a transmissive chain. The title al-Tabaqat al-saghir occurs twice, outside of an isnad (the relationship between the two Tabaqat works is a subject of some scholarly discussion). The simpler title, al-Tabaqat, is also attributed to Ibn ʿAsakir a handful of times (though more often to other authors who wrote such works). Meaning, that the vast number of times that Ibn ʿAsakir mentions Ibn Saʿd, he does so without direct reference to a work. This matters for both how Ibn ʿAsakir was working and for what he wanted his audience to know. The choice to cite people rather than books notwithstanding, the isnads in Table 2 might be helpful for understanding the transmission history of Ibn Saʿd’s book. Scholars today commonly refer to recensions by al-Husayn b. Fahm (d. 289/902), al-Harith b. Abi Usama (d. 282/895), and possibly, Ibn Abi ’l-Dunya (though the latter perhaps only for al-Tabaqat al-saghir, as argued by Jens Scheiner).6 The roles of the other tradents in Table 2 and Graph 1 need exploring. In particular, the parts played by Abu Muhammad al-Jawhari (d. 454/1062), Abu Ishaq al-Barmaki (d. 445/1053), Abu Bakr Muhammad b. ʿAbd al-Baqi (d. 535/1140), and Abu Ghalib (d. 527/1132) might be studied by collecting their transmissions from Ibn Saʿd to see whether contents within them might represent distinct pieces of the Tabaqat al-kabir. Do citations from a particular chain always come from the same part of Ibn Saʿd’s work? Are Ibn Saʿd citations possibly pulled from the sort of hadith booklets studied by Konrad Hirschler? As Jaques has argued for Ibn Ishaq’s (d. 151/767) Sira, we should also keep our minds open to the possibility that there was not one al-Tabaqat al-kabir, but possibly different versions produced by Ibn Saʿd himself. The citations of Ibn Saʿd, within the TMD, do not map easily to the reuse alignments we generate independently with passim.7 Why this might be the case is complicated, but seems to arise ultimately (and mostly) from a) the fact that Ibn ʿAsakir is working with various transmissions from Ibn Saʿd, and these might have been passed on in pieces through written notebooks or collations, as just mentioned (meaning, the transmission was highly mediated); b) the alignment data we have is based on a specific edition of Ibn Saʿd’s text held in the OpenITI. In other cases, when an author relied directly upon an earlier work, citations map much more easily to text reuse alignments. These points suggest that we should be exploring the way that Ibn ʿAsakir cites his information more generally (including the role of transmission from people versus books) and the extent to which distinct transmission chains that include authors of well-known and surviving works might belong to distinct pieces of their books. Does he have at hand books themselves, even if he does not typically cite them directly? Our lines of enquiry will help us to understand both the reception of Ibn Saʿd’s book, and also how an author such as Ibn ʿAsakir, in producing his massive book, went about his work. Before we can get started, though, we need to work on the names that feature in citations, and that is why named entity recognition, and the ability to cluster related chains of transmission, are so important. For computer scientists, this sort of work is part of a new stock-in-trade of the digital humanities. For historians, it takes time and patience and iteration. Creating lists of name variants is frankly best done with music running in the background and plans for an evening outside. Working on manuscripts, scholars develop skills, including the ability to read and differentiate different scripts. Patience is required. For understanding books in their digital format, named entity recognition might just be a parallel to this sort of work, with rewards aplenty. Notes The OpenITI file that we used for this chapter, 0571IbnCasakir.TarikhDimashq.JK000916-ara1, is based on the 80-volume, 1995-2001 Dar al-Fikr edition edited by ʿUmar al-ʿAmrawi and ʿAli Shiri, but excludes volumes 71-80. Volumes 71-74 represent a mustadrak, or amendment by the editors (including additional biographical entries); these volumes have now been added to the OpenITI file based on another file in the OpenITI containing the entire Dar al-Fikr work (0571IbnCasakir.TarikhDimashq.Shamela000071-ara1, containing 8.5 million words). Volumes 75-80 represent indices (not added). Gowaart Van Den Bossche and Hamid Reza Hakimi annotated the file for the KITAB project. &amp;#8617; See e.g., Jens Scheiner,  ‘Ibn ʿAsakir’s Virtual Library as Reflected in His TMD,’ in New Perspectives on Ibn ʿAsakir in Islamic Historiography, ed. Steven Judd and Scheiner (Leiden: Brill, 2017), pp. 156-257, esp. at pp. 179-82. &amp;#8617; ‘Regular expressions’ is the name of a formalized way of constructing search patterns, implemented in many computer languages and much text editing software. Regular expressions can be used, for example, to allow for intervening words or to locate passages that cross pages or other boundaries. See Jan Goyvaerts and Steven Levithan, Regular Expressions Cookbook, 2nd. rev. ed. (Farnham: O’Reilly, 2012). &amp;#8617; There were also isnads with between 7 and 12 transmitters within them, but 6 nodes was by far the most common. &amp;#8617; For reflections on varieties of names in another context, and challenges of pinning names to titles, see Konrad Hirschler, A Monument to Medieval Syrian Book Culture: The Library of Ibn ʻAbd al-Hadi (Edinburgh: Edinburgh University Press, 2020), pp. 177-78. &amp;#8617; Scheiner, ‘Ibn ʿAsakir’s Virtual Library,’ p. 181-82 and p. 269. I use death dates for tradents from Scheiner and from Ahmad Nazir Atassi, ‘The transmission of Ibn Saʿd’s biographical dictionary Kitab al-tabaqāt al-kabir,’ Journal of Arabic and Islamic Studies(2012), pp. 56–80. &amp;#8617; Atassi has noted that ‘expecting a verbatim match between the reports found in a consulted compilation and the corresponding report in the printed [al-Tabaqat al-kabir] is unrealistic.’ ‘The transmission of Ibn Saʿd’s biographical dictionary,’ p. 73. &amp;#8617;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Between Manuscripts and Digital Texts: Commentaries on Hadith Raʾs al-Jalut</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/09-30.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Between Manuscripts and Digital Texts: Commentaries on Hadith Raʾs al-Jalut" /><published>2020-09-30T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-09-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/Between%20Manuscripts%20and%20Digital%20Texts-%20Commentaries%20on%20Hadith%20Ra%CA%BEs%20al-Jalut</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/09-30.html">&lt;p&gt;As digital historians and corpus curators, faced with the complex history of reception and transmission as well as the distinct approach to learning and authorship, attributing authors to premodern Islamicate texts and representing this complexity within our corpus metadata is often a challenging task. Especially daunting for composite texts, commentaries, and super-commentaries, the task is no less challenging when it comes to working with printed editions and online digital libraries, since we face the risk of reproducing editorial choices, and biases, whether knowingly or unknowingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most scholars are as cautious about digital editions as they are about uncritical printed editions. The manuscript, not the printed edition, is seen as the least mediated and most reliable link with the author, because even the most carefully edited texts are not free from editorial interventions. Most readers will be inclined to ignore the critical apparatus and go with the editor’s preference. Digital editions and e-books, however, tend to omit the critical apparatus. Moreover, many digital texts are typed by hand, and their origin and ‘witness’ printed editions are obscure. This adds to the challenges of curating a digital corpus with reliable metadata. In addition to text reuse data, accurate metadata is essential for mapping the Islamicate written heritage in a way that reflects its intertextuality and discursiveness. During the ongoing pandemic physical libraries were not accessible for several months, which created a perfect occasion to reflect on the reliability of digital texts available on the Internet. I will share the case of a modern gloss (&lt;em&gt;taʿliqa&lt;/em&gt;) on a seventeenth-century hadith commentary (&lt;em&gt;sharh hadith&lt;/em&gt;) in the OpenITI, and follow its journey from manuscript libraries to print, to online digital libraries, and finally to our corpus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;al-taʿliqa-ʿala-al-fawaʾid-al-radawiyya-a-gloss-on-a-commentary&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Al-Taʿliqa ʿala al-Fawaʾid al-Radawiyya:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;A Gloss on a Commentary&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Author assignment issues are common in OpenITI corpus metadata, and are often settled easily. However, my chance encounter with a text titled &lt;em&gt;al-Taʿliqa ʿala al-Fawaʾid al-Radawiyya&lt;/em&gt; took me on a longer journey than expected. &lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Taʿliqa&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;em&gt;Gloss&lt;/em&gt;), which originated from the Shia Online Library (&lt;a href=&quot;http://shiaonlinelibrary.com/&quot;&gt;http://shiaonlinelibrary.com&lt;/a&gt;), was assigned in the metadata to the Safavid polymath Qadi Saʿid al-Qummi (d. after 1107/1695), known as &lt;em&gt;Hakim-i Kuchek&lt;/em&gt; (The Lesser Sage), who was a student of the famous traditionist Mulla Muhsin Fayd-i Kashani (d. ca. 1091/1680), and personal physician to Shah ʿAbbas II (r. 1052-77/1642-66). After going through the text, I realised that the metadata, as captured below in Figure 1, was misleading. The text was dominated by &lt;em&gt;glosses&lt;/em&gt; by the leader of the Islamic Revolution of Iran, Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini (d. 1989), on Qadi Saʿid al-Qummi’s original text. Qadi Saʿid al-Qummi’s  text was a commentary on a short dialogue between the eighth Twelver Shi’i imam ʿAli b. Musa al-Rida (d. 203/818) and a Jewish Exilarch (Raʾs al-Jalut = Resh Galuta in Hebrew). The intriguing glosses by the young Ruhollah Khomeini, written in August 1929 during a summer retreat “from the glorious Qum, due to the heat  and suspension of classes,” in his hometown of Khomein, included an introduction and a conclusion, as well as substantial comments and even objections to Qadi Saʿid al-Qummi. It was clear that the &lt;em&gt;Taʿliqa&lt;/em&gt; should be attributed to Khomeini, the last commentator, rather than to Saʿid al-Qummi. The metadata of the digital library thus omitted the history of the commentary tradition, and only partially corresponded to the manuscript and to the printed edition. If we take a closer look at the reception of the &lt;em&gt;Sharh&lt;/em&gt; and the manuscript tradition, it will become clear why metadata matters for corpus analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(See below screenshots from Shia Online Library and OpenITI corpus).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/old_posts/Image-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 1&lt;/strong&gt;. Shia Online Library assigns the &lt;em&gt;Taʿliqa&lt;/em&gt; to Saʿid al-Qummi despite the printed edition’s attribution of the text to Ruhollah Khomeini.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/old_posts/Image-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 2.&lt;/strong&gt; A screenshot of the OpenITI corpus metadata prior to correction. Now the application has Ruhollah Khomeini as the author, since we list the final author within the application. (See the KITAB Corpus Arabic Metadata App at &lt;a href=&quot;https://kitab-corpus-metadata.azurewebsites.net/&quot;&gt;https://kitab-corpus-metadata.azurewebsites.net&lt;/a&gt;). Users can also report similar mistakes via the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/old_posts/Image-3.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 3.&lt;/strong&gt; The completed YML-form of the &lt;em&gt;Taʿliqa&lt;/em&gt; in the OpenITI corpus. Curating the corpus includes annotating, creating reliable metadata, reporting issues, and vetting by the KITAB team. The updated URI is 1409RuhAllahKhumayni.TacliqaCalaFawaidRadawiyya.Shia04006-ara1&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-manuscript-tradition&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Manuscript Tradition&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sharh Hadith Raʾs al-Jalut,&lt;/em&gt; originally titled &lt;em&gt;al-Fawaʾid al-Radawiyya,&lt;/em&gt; is a treatise by Saʿid al-Qummi from his incomplete &lt;em&gt;Arbaʿinat (&lt;/em&gt;forty treatises on various subjects), which has been published separately. It constitutes al-Qummi’s commentary on ʿAli b. Musa al-Rida’s answers to questions asked by the Jewish Exilarch. While overwhelming and converting a Jewish scholar is a known topos in Muslim literature, the presence of a Jewish Exiliarch in a medieval Muslim society is not a fiction. Geniza materials testify that the office of Exiliarch continued at least until the fall of Baghdad to the Mongols in 1258 (Gafni, 1999). More elaborate versions of the interreligious debates of Imam Rida at the court of al-Maʾmun were first related by Ibn Babawayh (d. 329/991) in his &lt;em&gt;Kitab al-Tawhid&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;ʿUyun akhbar al-Rida&lt;/em&gt;. These debates are well known and have been analysed by several scholars (Wassertrom, 1995; Wasserstein, 1999; Cooperson, 2004; Sahner, 2019). It is however this short enigmatic version preserved by al-Qummi that gave rise to a separate commentary tradition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only nine commentaries on &lt;em&gt;Hadith Raʾs al-Jalut&lt;/em&gt; had been previously identified (Muhammad Rida Husayni, 1999). Via the recently launched online manuscript catalogue by the National Library and Archives of Iran (NLAI) (&lt;a href=&quot;https://hmi.nlai.ir/&quot;&gt;https://hmi.nlai.ir/&lt;/a&gt;), I have located 15 different commentaries bringing the total number of records of different manuscripts of the commentaries to 132, most of them authored and copied during the 19&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century (12&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt;-13&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; centuries AH) in Iran. This online catalogue, which is based on previously published catalogues, is very rich, but still lacks some essential metadata information, such as the authors’ dates of death or the language of the text. There are also identical records, for no apparent reason, such as 8 duplicates for various manuscripts of the &lt;em&gt;Sharh&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Hadith Raʾs  al-Jalut.&lt;/em&gt; Of course, given the challenges of this material and the current state of research, one assumes that not all manuscripts included in compilations have been correctly identified and catalogued. Nonetheless, the “National  Memory of the Iranians” Project of the NLAI, which catalogues more than 1 million manuscripts from 1,868 libraries around the world, is unparalleled in its scope and ambition and I think the present exercise proves this point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To have an idea about the diversity and complexity of the hadith commentary tradition, let us look at the following example (&lt;strong&gt;Figure 4&lt;/strong&gt;). Here, Saʿid al-Qummi’s late 17th-century commentary is written on the margins of Ahmad b. Zayn al-Din al-Ahsaʾi’s 19th-century commentary, in 1934 (1313 Persian solar calendar) by a certain Murtada b. Muhammad Sadiq al-Tabasi, known as Farhang. This use of the margins is hardly because of the shortage of paper in Tehran at the time. Farhang clearly thought the two texts should be read together. However, this kind of intertextuality, fluidity, and discursiveness, which is characteristic of the manuscript culture, almost always becomes obsolete after the transition to printing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/old_posts/Image-4.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 4.&lt;/strong&gt; The beginning of Shaykh Ahmad al-Ahsaʾi’s &lt;em&gt;Sharh&lt;/em&gt; from a composite manuscript (&lt;em&gt;Rasaʾil,&lt;/em&gt; mostly by al-Ahsaʾi, copied in 1821, in Rubat-i Pusht-i Badam village, Yazd province) with Saʿid al-Qummi’s commentary written on the margins of fol. 126b-142a more than a century later in Tehran (1934). Courtesy of Princeton University Library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Commentators&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date of death&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Titles&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Number of manuscript copies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Qadi Saʿid al-Qummi, Muhammad-Saʿid b. Muhammad-Mufid&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1107/1695&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Al-Fawaʾid al-Radawiyya&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;63&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Mulla ʿAbd al-Rahim b. Muhammad-Yunus  al-Damawandi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;1158/1745&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sharh Hadith  Raʾs al-Jalut&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Mulla Mahdi b. Abi Dhar al-Naraqi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1210/1795&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sharh Hadith  Raʾs al-Jalut&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Mirza Abu’l-Qasim b. Hasan al-Jilani al-Qummi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1231/1816&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sharh Hadith  Raʾs al-Jalut&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;18&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Muhammad-Baqir b. Muhammad, Mullabashi Shirazi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1240/1824&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sharh Hadith  Raʾs al-Jalut&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shaykh Ahmad b. Zayn al-Din al-Ahsaʾi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1243/1826&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sharh Hadith  Raʾs al-Jalut&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;19&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Shaykh Muhammad b. Haj Muhammad-Hasan al-Mashhadi al-Tusi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1257/1841&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ghanimat al-Hijaz fi hall al-alghaz&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Muhammad-Ismaʿil b. Muhammad-Jaʿfar al-Isfahani&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1280/1863&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sharh Hadith  Raʾs al-Jalut&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Mulla Muhammad b. Ahmad b. Mulla Mahdi al-Naraqi, known as ʿAbd al-Sahib&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1297/1880&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sharh Hadith  Raʾs al-Jalut&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Muhammad-Hasan b. Ahmad Nazari&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;fl. 13th/19th century&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sharh Hadith  Raʾs al-Jalut&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Najafquli Anjudani&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;fl. 13th/19th century&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sharh Hadith  Raʾs al-Jalut&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Sayyid-ʿAli b. Muhammad-ʿAli, Husayni Meybudi&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; 1313/1895&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sharh Hadith  Raʾs al-Jalut&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;13&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; Muhammad-Husayn b. ʿAbd Allah al-Isfahani&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1362/1943?&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sharh Hadith  Raʾs al-Jalut&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;14&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Anonymous&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sharh Hadith  Raʾs al-Jalut&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;1409/1989&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;al-Taʿliqa ʿala al-Fawaʾid al-Radawiyya&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;132&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Table 1.&lt;/strong&gt; A list of all known commentaries on &lt;em&gt;Hadith Raʾs al-Jalut&lt;/em&gt; with the  number of manuscripts that I could locate for each commentary in manuscript libraries (including multitext compilations). The earliest was written by Qadi Saʿid al-Qummi in 1099/1688, while the last one, Khomeini’s &lt;em&gt;Taʿliqa,&lt;/em&gt; was written in 1348/1929.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my knowledge, only three of the above-listed commentaries, including Khomeini’s &lt;em&gt;Taʿliqa,&lt;/em&gt;  have been published  (see References below). These are also available in digital format. Some manuscripts are probably still uncatalogued and unknown. For instance, just 5 commentaries were identified by Agha Buzurg Tehrani (d. 1970) in his comprehensive &lt;em&gt;al-Dhariʿa ila Tasanif al-Shiʿa.&lt;/em&gt; Only with the rapid digitalisation we are beginning to get a better view of the Islamicate textual tradition. But we have yet to fully realise how our understanding  of premodern book culture has been formed, and in many  ways limited, by what is available in print. Let us consider some of these limitations taking the &lt;em&gt;Taʿliqa&lt;/em&gt; as an example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-digital-text-of-the-taʿliqa-in-the-openiti-corpus&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Digital Text of the &lt;em&gt;Taʿliqa&lt;/em&gt; in the OpenITI corpus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The digital text of the &lt;em&gt;Taʿliqa&lt;/em&gt; fin our corpus has inherited several deficiencies from the printed edition, on which it is based, and adds more:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The text of the original commentary by Saʿid al-Qummi and the gloss by Ruhollah Khomeini are not marked clearly.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The original colophon by the author and a note by the copyist, a certain al-Lawasani, are both present, but they are not marked clearly. In this case, the printed edition follows the manuscript copy.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In the manuscript, the glosses are reproduced on the margins of the original commentary, which is not how they are reproduced in printed editions. Glosses are either moved to footnotes, or printed on the same page  following  the main text, sometimes without proper visual signposts, which is the case with the present edition. This makes it difficult to see where the &lt;em&gt;Sharh&lt;/em&gt; ends and where the &lt;em&gt;Taʿliqa&lt;/em&gt; begins. The digital text in the OpenITI, which is based on this edition, thus presents challenges for computational analysis. On the other hand, digital technology provides exciting possibilities for visual presentation of the text, including side by side reading, which will be available for the  OpenITI in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The metadata consists only of the title of the book and the name of the original commentator (Qadi Saʿid al-Qummi). Other essential information about him and the second commentator (Ruhollah Khomeini); the dates and places of writing and copying (i.e. Isfahan, 14 Rabiʿ al-Awwal 1099 AH or Khomein, 22 Rabiʿ al-Awwal, 1348 AH); the provenance of the manuscript; genre; topics; etc. is not provided.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the ideal case scenario, all extant texts and commentaries of the ‘hadith Raʾs al-Jalut’ should be included in the corpus, including the version preserved and commented upon by Saʿid al-Qummi, and the more distant and complete versions of the debates by Shaykh Saduq in his &lt;em&gt;Kitab al-Tawhid&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;ʿUyun akhbar al-Rida.&lt;/em&gt; Secondly, all the commentaries (more than a dozen, mostly in manuscript form) should be transcribed and converted  into machine-readable format, added to the corpus, and the relationship between the texts should be recorded in the metadata. It is worth noting that the commentaries engage with other material besides strictly Shiʿi doctrines. As we can see from the citations and references in al-Qummi’s &lt;em&gt;Commentary&lt;/em&gt; and Khomeini’s &lt;em&gt;Gloss,&lt;/em&gt; the authors are not only in conversation with the Qur’an, the Prophet and the Shiʿi imams, but are also in conversation with Aristotle, Neo-Platonists, the Ikhwan al-Safa, Ibn ʿArabi, post-classical Muslim philosophers and mystics among others. This is where the strength of text reuse method in mapping the intellectual tradition comes in. The real potential of the corpus approach and distant reading, of course, lies in the ability to go through a vast number of books and return all potentially related material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, after I raised the issue via an online system, the corpus manager, Lorenz Nigst, implemented the changes to the authorship of the work in the URI and metadata. In more ambiguous cases, the issue would be discussed at one of the corpus meetings with team members. To facilitate further research, all relevant information about the transmission of the text, authorship, provenance, and its explicit relationship to other texts in the corpus (e.g. between al-Ghazali’s &lt;em&gt;Tahafut al-falasifa&lt;/em&gt; and Ibn Rushd’s response, &lt;em&gt;Tahafut al-Tahafut&lt;/em&gt;) are recorded in the metadata. That being said, the attribution of a unique identifier (URI) and metadata constitutes neither a final verdict nor a scholarly position on the authorship of a given text. By checking for quality and consistency of the metadata, the project team  hopes to ensure the reliability of the corpus as a starting point for researchers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The case of &lt;em&gt;Hadith Raʾs al-Jalut&lt;/em&gt; thus illustrates the challenges of corpus-building and referencing of Islamicate texts in a way that reflects the history of their reception and transmission. Specifically, it highlights the complexities of assigning authorship to composite materials such as commentaries and glosses. Engaging with the content of the commentaries, while beyond the scope of this blog, would also reveal that hadith commentaries are highly intertextual and engage with a variety of topics and disciplines, including philosophy and mysticism. Moreover, hadith commentary is a living and discursive Islamic tradition that flourishes to date. Finally, this example reminds us of the fact that most hadith commentaries are still in manuscript form, while modern commentaries, especially those on the digital platforms and TV channels, are  increasing by the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;references-to-primary-sources&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References to  primary sources&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Khomeini, Ruhollah. &lt;em&gt;al-Taʿliqa ʿalā al-Fawaʾid al-Radawiyya,&lt;/em&gt; 2nd edition&lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; Tehran, 1378/1999.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Husayni, Sayyid Muhammad-Rida. “Sharh-i Hadith-i Raʾs al-Jalut”, &lt;em&gt;Mirath-i Hadith-i Shiʿa&lt;/em&gt; 2 (1378/1999), pp. 233-54. This is an edition of  Mulla ʿAbd al-Sahib al-Naraqi’s commentary with a short introduction by the  editor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;al-Qummi, Ibn Babawayh. &lt;em&gt;Kitab al-Tawhid,&lt;/em&gt; ed. Sayyid Hashim al-Husayni al-Tihrani, Beirut, n.d., pp. 417-41; &lt;em&gt;ʿUyun akhbar al-Rida,&lt;/em&gt; Qum,  1378/1999, vol. 1, pp. 139-82. For the earliest records of debates between Imam Rida and the Jewish Exilarch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;al-Qummi, Qadi Saʿid. &lt;em&gt;al-Arbaʿinat li-kashf anwar qudsiyyat,&lt;/em&gt; ed. Najafquli Habibi, Tehran, 1381/2002. The treatise discussed in this blog was published in this collection.  Al-Qummi’s magnum opus, a three-volume commentary on Ibn Babawayh’s hadith collection, the &lt;em&gt;Sharh Tawhid al-Saduq&lt;/em&gt;, exists in a digital edition and is currently being added to the OpenITI corpus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;studies-and-reference-works&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Studies and reference works&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cooperson, Michael. &lt;em&gt;Classical Arabic Biography: The Heirs of the Prophet in the Age of al-Maʾmun,&lt;/em&gt; Cambridge, 2004, pp. &lt;em&gt;7&lt;/em&gt;0-106.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gafni, Isaiah M. “Exilarch,” &lt;em&gt;Encyclopaedia Iranica,&lt;/em&gt; online edition, 199, available online at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iranicaonline.org/articles/exilarch&quot;&gt;https://www.iranicaonline.org/articles/exilarch&lt;/a&gt; (accessed on 24 September 2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rizvi, Sajjad H. “Qāżi Saʿid Qomi,&lt;em&gt;” Encyclopaedia Iranica&lt;/em&gt;, online edition, 2005, available at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.iranicaonline.org/articles/qazi-said-qomi&quot;&gt;http://www.iranicaonline.org/articles/qazi-said-qomi&lt;/a&gt; (accessed on 20 September 2020).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sahner, Christian. “A Zoroastrian Dispute in the Caliph’s Court: The Gizistag Abalis in its Early Islamic Context,” &lt;em&gt;Iranian Studies&lt;/em&gt; 52:1-2 (2019), pp. 61-83, 69-70.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tehrani, Agha Buzurg. &lt;em&gt;al-Dhariʿa ila Tasanif al-Shiʿa,&lt;/em&gt; Beirut, 1983. A comprehensive mid-twentieth century bibliography of Shiʿi works, which includes some of the commentaries known to the author. See volumes 13: 199/696, 16: 70/349, 16: 340/1581, 26: 285/1423.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wasserstein, David J. “The ‘Majlis of al-Rida’: A Religious Debate in the Court of the Caliph al-Maʾmun as Represented in a Shiʿi Hagiographical Work about the Eighth Imam ʿAli ibn Musa Al-Rida,” in Hava Lazarus-Yafeh et al (eds), &lt;em&gt;The Majlis: Interreligious Encounters in Medieval Islam,&lt;/em&gt; Wiesbaden, 1999, pp. 108-119.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wasserstrom, Steven M. &lt;em&gt;Between Muslim and Jew: The Problem of Symbiosis Under Early Islam,&lt;/em&gt; Princeton, 1995, pp. 113-119.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Aslisho Qurboniev</name></author><summary type="html">As digital historians and corpus curators, faced with the complex history of reception and transmission as well as the distinct approach to learning and authorship, attributing authors to premodern Islamicate texts and representing this complexity within our corpus metadata is often a challenging task. Especially daunting for composite texts, commentaries, and super-commentaries, the task is no less challenging when it comes to working with printed editions and online digital libraries, since we face the risk of reproducing editorial choices, and biases, whether knowingly or unknowingly. Most scholars are as cautious about digital editions as they are about uncritical printed editions. The manuscript, not the printed edition, is seen as the least mediated and most reliable link with the author, because even the most carefully edited texts are not free from editorial interventions. Most readers will be inclined to ignore the critical apparatus and go with the editor’s preference. Digital editions and e-books, however, tend to omit the critical apparatus. Moreover, many digital texts are typed by hand, and their origin and ‘witness’ printed editions are obscure. This adds to the challenges of curating a digital corpus with reliable metadata. In addition to text reuse data, accurate metadata is essential for mapping the Islamicate written heritage in a way that reflects its intertextuality and discursiveness. During the ongoing pandemic physical libraries were not accessible for several months, which created a perfect occasion to reflect on the reliability of digital texts available on the Internet. I will share the case of a modern gloss (taʿliqa) on a seventeenth-century hadith commentary (sharh hadith) in the OpenITI, and follow its journey from manuscript libraries to print, to online digital libraries, and finally to our corpus.  Al-Taʿliqa ʿala al-Fawaʾid al-Radawiyya: A Gloss on a Commentary Author assignment issues are common in OpenITI corpus metadata, and are often settled easily. However, my chance encounter with a text titled al-Taʿliqa ʿala al-Fawaʾid al-Radawiyya took me on a longer journey than expected.  The Taʿliqa (Gloss), which originated from the Shia Online Library (http://shiaonlinelibrary.com), was assigned in the metadata to the Safavid polymath Qadi Saʿid al-Qummi (d. after 1107/1695), known as Hakim-i Kuchek (The Lesser Sage), who was a student of the famous traditionist Mulla Muhsin Fayd-i Kashani (d. ca. 1091/1680), and personal physician to Shah ʿAbbas II (r. 1052-77/1642-66). After going through the text, I realised that the metadata, as captured below in Figure 1, was misleading. The text was dominated by glosses by the leader of the Islamic Revolution of Iran, Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini (d. 1989), on Qadi Saʿid al-Qummi’s original text. Qadi Saʿid al-Qummi’s  text was a commentary on a short dialogue between the eighth Twelver Shi’i imam ʿAli b. Musa al-Rida (d. 203/818) and a Jewish Exilarch (Raʾs al-Jalut = Resh Galuta in Hebrew). The intriguing glosses by the young Ruhollah Khomeini, written in August 1929 during a summer retreat “from the glorious Qum, due to the heat  and suspension of classes,” in his hometown of Khomein, included an introduction and a conclusion, as well as substantial comments and even objections to Qadi Saʿid al-Qummi. It was clear that the Taʿliqa should be attributed to Khomeini, the last commentator, rather than to Saʿid al-Qummi. The metadata of the digital library thus omitted the history of the commentary tradition, and only partially corresponded to the manuscript and to the printed edition. If we take a closer look at the reception of the Sharh and the manuscript tradition, it will become clear why metadata matters for corpus analysis. (See below screenshots from Shia Online Library and OpenITI corpus). Figure 1. Shia Online Library assigns the Taʿliqa to Saʿid al-Qummi despite the printed edition’s attribution of the text to Ruhollah Khomeini. Figure 2. A screenshot of the OpenITI corpus metadata prior to correction. Now the application has Ruhollah Khomeini as the author, since we list the final author within the application. (See the KITAB Corpus Arabic Metadata App at https://kitab-corpus-metadata.azurewebsites.net). Users can also report similar mistakes via the system. Figure 3. The completed YML-form of the Taʿliqa in the OpenITI corpus. Curating the corpus includes annotating, creating reliable metadata, reporting issues, and vetting by the KITAB team. The updated URI is 1409RuhAllahKhumayni.TacliqaCalaFawaidRadawiyya.Shia04006-ara1 The Manuscript Tradition Sharh Hadith Raʾs al-Jalut, originally titled al-Fawaʾid al-Radawiyya, is a treatise by Saʿid al-Qummi from his incomplete Arbaʿinat (forty treatises on various subjects), which has been published separately. It constitutes al-Qummi’s commentary on ʿAli b. Musa al-Rida’s answers to questions asked by the Jewish Exilarch. While overwhelming and converting a Jewish scholar is a known topos in Muslim literature, the presence of a Jewish Exiliarch in a medieval Muslim society is not a fiction. Geniza materials testify that the office of Exiliarch continued at least until the fall of Baghdad to the Mongols in 1258 (Gafni, 1999). More elaborate versions of the interreligious debates of Imam Rida at the court of al-Maʾmun were first related by Ibn Babawayh (d. 329/991) in his Kitab al-Tawhid and ʿUyun akhbar al-Rida. These debates are well known and have been analysed by several scholars (Wassertrom, 1995; Wasserstein, 1999; Cooperson, 2004; Sahner, 2019). It is however this short enigmatic version preserved by al-Qummi that gave rise to a separate commentary tradition. Only nine commentaries on Hadith Raʾs al-Jalut had been previously identified (Muhammad Rida Husayni, 1999). Via the recently launched online manuscript catalogue by the National Library and Archives of Iran (NLAI) (https://hmi.nlai.ir/), I have located 15 different commentaries bringing the total number of records of different manuscripts of the commentaries to 132, most of them authored and copied during the 19th century (12th-13th centuries AH) in Iran. This online catalogue, which is based on previously published catalogues, is very rich, but still lacks some essential metadata information, such as the authors’ dates of death or the language of the text. There are also identical records, for no apparent reason, such as 8 duplicates for various manuscripts of the Sharh Hadith Raʾs  al-Jalut. Of course, given the challenges of this material and the current state of research, one assumes that not all manuscripts included in compilations have been correctly identified and catalogued. Nonetheless, the “National  Memory of the Iranians” Project of the NLAI, which catalogues more than 1 million manuscripts from 1,868 libraries around the world, is unparalleled in its scope and ambition and I think the present exercise proves this point. To have an idea about the diversity and complexity of the hadith commentary tradition, let us look at the following example (Figure 4). Here, Saʿid al-Qummi’s late 17th-century commentary is written on the margins of Ahmad b. Zayn al-Din al-Ahsaʾi’s 19th-century commentary, in 1934 (1313 Persian solar calendar) by a certain Murtada b. Muhammad Sadiq al-Tabasi, known as Farhang. This use of the margins is hardly because of the shortage of paper in Tehran at the time. Farhang clearly thought the two texts should be read together. However, this kind of intertextuality, fluidity, and discursiveness, which is characteristic of the manuscript culture, almost always becomes obsolete after the transition to printing. Figure 4. The beginning of Shaykh Ahmad al-Ahsaʾi’s Sharh from a composite manuscript (Rasaʾil, mostly by al-Ahsaʾi, copied in 1821, in Rubat-i Pusht-i Badam village, Yazd province) with Saʿid al-Qummi’s commentary written on the margins of fol. 126b-142a more than a century later in Tehran (1934). Courtesy of Princeton University Library.   Commentators Date of death Titles Number of manuscript copies 1 Qadi Saʿid al-Qummi, Muhammad-Saʿid b. Muhammad-Mufid 1107/1695 Al-Fawaʾid al-Radawiyya 63 2 Mulla ʿAbd al-Rahim b. Muhammad-Yunus  al-Damawandi  1158/1745 Sharh Hadith  Raʾs al-Jalut 7 3 Mulla Mahdi b. Abi Dhar al-Naraqi 1210/1795 Sharh Hadith  Raʾs al-Jalut 2 4 Mirza Abu’l-Qasim b. Hasan al-Jilani al-Qummi 1231/1816 Sharh Hadith  Raʾs al-Jalut 18 5 Muhammad-Baqir b. Muhammad, Mullabashi Shirazi 1240/1824 Sharh Hadith  Raʾs al-Jalut 3 6 Shaykh Ahmad b. Zayn al-Din al-Ahsaʾi 1243/1826 Sharh Hadith  Raʾs al-Jalut 19 7 Shaykh Muhammad b. Haj Muhammad-Hasan al-Mashhadi al-Tusi 1257/1841 Ghanimat al-Hijaz fi hall al-alghaz 1 8 Muhammad-Ismaʿil b. Muhammad-Jaʿfar al-Isfahani 1280/1863 Sharh Hadith  Raʾs al-Jalut 2 9 Mulla Muhammad b. Ahmad b. Mulla Mahdi al-Naraqi, known as ʿAbd al-Sahib 1297/1880 Sharh Hadith  Raʾs al-Jalut 5 10 Muhammad-Hasan b. Ahmad Nazari fl. 13th/19th century Sharh Hadith  Raʾs al-Jalut 2 11 Najafquli Anjudani fl. 13th/19th century Sharh Hadith  Raʾs al-Jalut 1 12 Sayyid-ʿAli b. Muhammad-ʿAli, Husayni Meybudi  1313/1895 Sharh Hadith  Raʾs al-Jalut 2 13  Muhammad-Husayn b. ʿAbd Allah al-Isfahani 1362/1943? Sharh Hadith  Raʾs al-Jalut 3 14 Anonymous   Sharh Hadith  Raʾs al-Jalut 3 15 Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini 1409/1989 al-Taʿliqa ʿala al-Fawaʾid al-Radawiyya 1   Total     132 Table 1. A list of all known commentaries on Hadith Raʾs al-Jalut with the  number of manuscripts that I could locate for each commentary in manuscript libraries (including multitext compilations). The earliest was written by Qadi Saʿid al-Qummi in 1099/1688, while the last one, Khomeini’s Taʿliqa, was written in 1348/1929. To my knowledge, only three of the above-listed commentaries, including Khomeini’s Taʿliqa,  have been published  (see References below). These are also available in digital format. Some manuscripts are probably still uncatalogued and unknown. For instance, just 5 commentaries were identified by Agha Buzurg Tehrani (d. 1970) in his comprehensive al-Dhariʿa ila Tasanif al-Shiʿa. Only with the rapid digitalisation we are beginning to get a better view of the Islamicate textual tradition. But we have yet to fully realise how our understanding  of premodern book culture has been formed, and in many  ways limited, by what is available in print. Let us consider some of these limitations taking the Taʿliqa as an example. The Digital Text of the Taʿliqa in the OpenITI corpus The digital text of the Taʿliqa fin our corpus has inherited several deficiencies from the printed edition, on which it is based, and adds more: The text of the original commentary by Saʿid al-Qummi and the gloss by Ruhollah Khomeini are not marked clearly. The original colophon by the author and a note by the copyist, a certain al-Lawasani, are both present, but they are not marked clearly. In this case, the printed edition follows the manuscript copy. In the manuscript, the glosses are reproduced on the margins of the original commentary, which is not how they are reproduced in printed editions. Glosses are either moved to footnotes, or printed on the same page  following  the main text, sometimes without proper visual signposts, which is the case with the present edition. This makes it difficult to see where the Sharh ends and where the Taʿliqa begins. The digital text in the OpenITI, which is based on this edition, thus presents challenges for computational analysis. On the other hand, digital technology provides exciting possibilities for visual presentation of the text, including side by side reading, which will be available for the  OpenITI in the future. The metadata consists only of the title of the book and the name of the original commentator (Qadi Saʿid al-Qummi). Other essential information about him and the second commentator (Ruhollah Khomeini); the dates and places of writing and copying (i.e. Isfahan, 14 Rabiʿ al-Awwal 1099 AH or Khomein, 22 Rabiʿ al-Awwal, 1348 AH); the provenance of the manuscript; genre; topics; etc. is not provided. In the ideal case scenario, all extant texts and commentaries of the ‘hadith Raʾs al-Jalut’ should be included in the corpus, including the version preserved and commented upon by Saʿid al-Qummi, and the more distant and complete versions of the debates by Shaykh Saduq in his Kitab al-Tawhid and ʿUyun akhbar al-Rida. Secondly, all the commentaries (more than a dozen, mostly in manuscript form) should be transcribed and converted  into machine-readable format, added to the corpus, and the relationship between the texts should be recorded in the metadata. It is worth noting that the commentaries engage with other material besides strictly Shiʿi doctrines. As we can see from the citations and references in al-Qummi’s Commentary and Khomeini’s Gloss, the authors are not only in conversation with the Qur’an, the Prophet and the Shiʿi imams, but are also in conversation with Aristotle, Neo-Platonists, the Ikhwan al-Safa, Ibn ʿArabi, post-classical Muslim philosophers and mystics among others. This is where the strength of text reuse method in mapping the intellectual tradition comes in. The real potential of the corpus approach and distant reading, of course, lies in the ability to go through a vast number of books and return all potentially related material. In this case, after I raised the issue via an online system, the corpus manager, Lorenz Nigst, implemented the changes to the authorship of the work in the URI and metadata. In more ambiguous cases, the issue would be discussed at one of the corpus meetings with team members. To facilitate further research, all relevant information about the transmission of the text, authorship, provenance, and its explicit relationship to other texts in the corpus (e.g. between al-Ghazali’s Tahafut al-falasifa and Ibn Rushd’s response, Tahafut al-Tahafut) are recorded in the metadata. That being said, the attribution of a unique identifier (URI) and metadata constitutes neither a final verdict nor a scholarly position on the authorship of a given text. By checking for quality and consistency of the metadata, the project team  hopes to ensure the reliability of the corpus as a starting point for researchers. The case of Hadith Raʾs al-Jalut thus illustrates the challenges of corpus-building and referencing of Islamicate texts in a way that reflects the history of their reception and transmission. Specifically, it highlights the complexities of assigning authorship to composite materials such as commentaries and glosses. Engaging with the content of the commentaries, while beyond the scope of this blog, would also reveal that hadith commentaries are highly intertextual and engage with a variety of topics and disciplines, including philosophy and mysticism. Moreover, hadith commentary is a living and discursive Islamic tradition that flourishes to date. Finally, this example reminds us of the fact that most hadith commentaries are still in manuscript form, while modern commentaries, especially those on the digital platforms and TV channels, are  increasing by the day. References to  primary sources Khomeini, Ruhollah. al-Taʿliqa ʿalā al-Fawaʾid al-Radawiyya, 2nd edition, Tehran, 1378/1999. Husayni, Sayyid Muhammad-Rida. “Sharh-i Hadith-i Raʾs al-Jalut”, Mirath-i Hadith-i Shiʿa 2 (1378/1999), pp. 233-54. This is an edition of  Mulla ʿAbd al-Sahib al-Naraqi’s commentary with a short introduction by the  editor. al-Qummi, Ibn Babawayh. Kitab al-Tawhid, ed. Sayyid Hashim al-Husayni al-Tihrani, Beirut, n.d., pp. 417-41; ʿUyun akhbar al-Rida, Qum,  1378/1999, vol. 1, pp. 139-82. For the earliest records of debates between Imam Rida and the Jewish Exilarch. al-Qummi, Qadi Saʿid. al-Arbaʿinat li-kashf anwar qudsiyyat, ed. Najafquli Habibi, Tehran, 1381/2002. The treatise discussed in this blog was published in this collection.  Al-Qummi’s magnum opus, a three-volume commentary on Ibn Babawayh’s hadith collection, the Sharh Tawhid al-Saduq, exists in a digital edition and is currently being added to the OpenITI corpus. Studies and reference works Cooperson, Michael. Classical Arabic Biography: The Heirs of the Prophet in the Age of al-Maʾmun, Cambridge, 2004, pp. 70-106. Gafni, Isaiah M. “Exilarch,” Encyclopaedia Iranica, online edition, 199, available online at https://www.iranicaonline.org/articles/exilarch (accessed on 24 September 2020). Rizvi, Sajjad H. “Qāżi Saʿid Qomi,” Encyclopaedia Iranica, online edition, 2005, available at http://www.iranicaonline.org/articles/qazi-said-qomi (accessed on 20 September 2020). Sahner, Christian. “A Zoroastrian Dispute in the Caliph’s Court: The Gizistag Abalis in its Early Islamic Context,” Iranian Studies 52:1-2 (2019), pp. 61-83, 69-70. Tehrani, Agha Buzurg. al-Dhariʿa ila Tasanif al-Shiʿa, Beirut, 1983. A comprehensive mid-twentieth century bibliography of Shiʿi works, which includes some of the commentaries known to the author. See volumes 13: 199/696, 16: 70/349, 16: 340/1581, 26: 285/1423. Wasserstein, David J. “The ‘Majlis of al-Rida’: A Religious Debate in the Court of the Caliph al-Maʾmun as Represented in a Shiʿi Hagiographical Work about the Eighth Imam ʿAli ibn Musa Al-Rida,” in Hava Lazarus-Yafeh et al (eds), The Majlis: Interreligious Encounters in Medieval Islam, Wiesbaden, 1999, pp. 108-119. Wasserstrom, Steven M. Between Muslim and Jew: The Problem of Symbiosis Under Early Islam, Princeton, 1995, pp. 113-119.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Arabic Pasts: Histories and Historiographies Research workshop (October 22-24, 2020 London)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/09-29.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Arabic Pasts: Histories and Historiographies Research workshop (October 22-24, 2020 London)" /><published>2020-09-29T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-09-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/Arabic%20Pasts-%20Histories%20and%20Historiographies%20Research%20workshop%20(October%2022-24,%202020%20London)</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/09-29.html">&lt;p&gt;This annual exploratory and informal workshop offers the opportunity to reflect on history writing in Arabic. This year the event will be held online to allow compliance with current UK social distancing guidelines. We hope to welcome newcomers to the workshop and to encourage a lively discussion – please do register using the link below. The programme is exciting as ever, with 24 papers treating history writing from the ninth century up to the present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Papers will elucidate the following sorts of questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Through what practices of writing or otherwise encoding the past and of remembering and forgetting, have different groups in the Middle East and North Africa viewed their pasts? At different times and places, how have the significant contours, events and actors in their histories been seen? Was the significant past the same for court historians as for literary historians; for bureaucrats as for the military; for Sufis as for Muslim lawyers and Traditionists?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How did non-Muslims and Muslims, men and women, adherents of different sectarian or juristic traditions, or speakers of different languages, within societies that became Islamic imagine the shape and meaning of their specific societies own pasts, and their relation to the universal history of the Islamic community?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How have urban and rural people, workers and peasants, the religiously educated and the technocratic elite, developed different ways of writing, remembering, or commemorating particular events in, or the broad sweep of, local, national, or Islamichistory?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;In what ways do educational institutions, museums, media organizations and proponents of heritage use history writing in Arabic to shape loyalties and senses of belonging in the Middle East, North Africa, and Europe?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following colleagues will chair panels and facilitate conversation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Julia Bray, University of Oxford&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fozia Bora, University of Leeds&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Jaakko Hameen-Anttila, University of Edinburgh&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Konrad Hirschler, Freie Universit  Berlin&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Marie Legendre, University of Edinburgh&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Andrew Marsham, University of Cambridge&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Harry Munt, University of York&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arabic Pasts is co-organised by Hugh Kennedy (SOAS), James McDougall (Oxford), and Sarah Bowen Savant (AKU-ISMC).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Programme agenda:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://kitab-project.org/wp-content/uploads/2020/09/Arabic-Pasts-Schedule_2020-Programme-Agenda.docx.pdf&quot;&gt;Arabic Pasts Schedule 2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Booking is essential:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/109156285388&quot;&gt;please reserve your space &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Venue:&lt;/strong&gt; Online&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact:&lt;/strong&gt; ismc.events@aku.edu&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Anjum Alam</name></author><summary type="html">This annual exploratory and informal workshop offers the opportunity to reflect on history writing in Arabic. This year the event will be held online to allow compliance with current UK social distancing guidelines. We hope to welcome newcomers to the workshop and to encourage a lively discussion – please do register using the link below. The programme is exciting as ever, with 24 papers treating history writing from the ninth century up to the present. Papers will elucidate the following sorts of questions: Through what practices of writing or otherwise encoding the past and of remembering and forgetting, have different groups in the Middle East and North Africa viewed their pasts? At different times and places, how have the significant contours, events and actors in their histories been seen? Was the significant past the same for court historians as for literary historians; for bureaucrats as for the military; for Sufis as for Muslim lawyers and Traditionists? How did non-Muslims and Muslims, men and women, adherents of different sectarian or juristic traditions, or speakers of different languages, within societies that became Islamic imagine the shape and meaning of their specific societies own pasts, and their relation to the universal history of the Islamic community? How have urban and rural people, workers and peasants, the religiously educated and the technocratic elite, developed different ways of writing, remembering, or commemorating particular events in, or the broad sweep of, local, national, or Islamichistory? In what ways do educational institutions, museums, media organizations and proponents of heritage use history writing in Arabic to shape loyalties and senses of belonging in the Middle East, North Africa, and Europe? The following colleagues will chair panels and facilitate conversation: Julia Bray, University of Oxford Fozia Bora, University of Leeds Jaakko Hameen-Anttila, University of Edinburgh Konrad Hirschler, Freie Universit  Berlin Marie Legendre, University of Edinburgh Andrew Marsham, University of Cambridge Harry Munt, University of York Arabic Pasts is co-organised by Hugh Kennedy (SOAS), James McDougall (Oxford), and Sarah Bowen Savant (AKU-ISMC). Programme agenda: Arabic Pasts Schedule 2020 Booking is essential: please reserve your space  Venue: Online Contact: ismc.events@aku.edu</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Adventures in Alignments: Training an Algorithm to Recognise Text Reuse</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/08-07.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Adventures in Alignments: Training an Algorithm to Recognise Text Reuse" /><published>2020-08-07T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-08-07T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/Adventures%20in%20Alignments-%20Training%20an%20Algorithm%20to%20Recognise%20Text%20Reuse</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/08-07.html">&lt;p&gt;Text reuse is the term that we use to describe cases where one book shares verbatim material with another. Text reuse can be studied manually through the reading of texts in parallel, but it can also be detected computationally, using the passim algorithm. Computational approaches, which can compare thousands of books at once, can teach us many exciting things about Arabic book history that would be impossible through manual study. &lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In this blog, I would like to make some observations about passim’s outputs at the level of individual alignments (the paired passages produced by passim) rather than larger book relationships, and through them discuss how the human evaluation of passim’s outputs can improve the algorithm’s performance. A key point I would like to make here: passim is powerful, but it cannot understand the content of texts, sometimes leading it to identify cases of similarity between texts that do not constitute meaningful reuse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;identifying-meaningful-reuse&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Identifying meaningful reuse&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to detect reuse, the passim algorithm makes a series of assumptions about what constitutes meaningful reuse. To give two key examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The minimum number of words that need to be shared between two passages, for it to be considered a reuse case (the min-match parameter)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The maximum length of a gap between the shared words in two passages, before it is either broken into two reuse cases, or not considered a reuse case (the gap parameter)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If passim’s assumptions about the nature of meaningful reuse are incorrect, it will either output a large number of meaningless alignments, or it will miss cases of meaningful reuse. This is particularly an issue when passages contain similar names. Table 1 gives an example of the kind of alignments that are produced if the gap parameter is too long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ibn Saʿd, &lt;em&gt;Kitab Tabaqat al-Kubra&lt;/em&gt; (VIII: 91)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Al-Tabarī, &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh al-Rusul wa-l-Muluk&lt;/em&gt; (III: 167)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;u&gt;زينب بنت خزيمة بن الحارث بن عبد الله بن عمرو بن عبد مناف بن هلال بن عامر بن صعصعة&lt;/u&gt; وهي أم المساكين كانت تسمى بذلك في الجاهلية أخبرنا محمد بن عمر حدثنا محمد بن عبد الله عن الزهري قال كانت زينب بنت خزيمة الهلالية تدعى أم المساكين &lt;u&gt;وكانت&lt;/u&gt; &lt;u&gt;عند الطفيل بن الحارث بن المطلب&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;وممن لم يذكر هشام في خبره هذا ممن روى عن رسول الله ص أنه تزوجه من النساء زينب بنت خزيمة وهي التي يقال لها أم المساكين من بني عامر بن صعصعة وهي &lt;u&gt;زينب بنت خزيمة بن الحارث ابن عبد الله بن عمرو بن عبد مناف بن هلال بن عامر بن صعصعة&lt;/u&gt; &lt;u&gt;وكانت&lt;/u&gt; قبل رسول الله &lt;u&gt;عند الطفيل بن الحارث بن المطلب&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Table 1:&lt;/strong&gt; In this alignment passim has matched a biographical entry for Zaynab bt. Khuzayma (a wife of the Prophet) from Ibn Saʿd’s &lt;em&gt;Tabaqat&lt;/em&gt; with al-Tabari’s account of the Prophet’s marriage to Zaynab. You can see from the underlined words that passim has matched Zaynab’s full name, in addition to the phrase &lt;em&gt;‘ʿinda al-tifayli bin al-harithi bin al-mutallibi’.&lt;/em&gt; In addition, passim may have identified that both passages use Zaynab’s epithet &lt;em&gt;‘umm al-masakin’&lt;/em&gt; (highlighted). Because a large gap has been allowed in the first passage between Zaynab’s full name and the final shared lines, the two matched passages are not meaningfully related.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For any clear understanding of the nature of text reuse in our corpus, we must ensure that passim locates the maximum possible instances of text reuse, without falsely identifying instances such as in the example above. One solution is to computationally locate names of individuals within the texts  and then exclude those from passim’s analysis. This is currently being explored by Ryan Muther through the automatic detection of isnads (see further, &lt;a href=&quot;/2020/02-03.html&quot;&gt;Tracking Traditions: Identifying Isnads in the OpenITI Corpus&lt;/a&gt;). Additionally, it is important to establish a set of ground truths against which to evaluate passim’s performance and experiment with different parameters. This is done through the manual annotation of text reuse and/or correction of passim alignments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-process-of-creating-evaluation-data&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The process of creating evaluation data&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My research is concerned with identifying cases of text reuse in order to understand the survival of ‘lost’ Fatimid texts into the fifteenth century. For this research, I read through and closely compared texts that describe a 10-year period of Fatimid history. This led me to identify an instance of significant reuse between two texts by the famous Mamluk historian al-Maqrizi (d. 1442): the &lt;em&gt;Ittiʿaz al-Hunafaʾ&lt;/em&gt; (a chronicle history of the Fatimids) and the &lt;em&gt;kitab al-Muqaffa al-Kabir&lt;/em&gt; (a biographical dictionary). An exhaustive comparison of sections of these two works identified instances of text reuse, which could be used to evaluate passim’s performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Passim was run on the chosen pair of books, and tags were inserted identifying where passim had located passages of reuse. These tags are in pairs, constituting a beginning and an end tag with a shared unique identifier (UI) number (e.g. @ALIGN@B@2@ and @ALIGN@E@2@). The UI number is specific to the passage as it is tagged in both books. Figure 1 gives an example of the tags in parallel texts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/old_posts/MB2-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 1&lt;/strong&gt; A side-by-side view of corresponding automatic alignment tags in al-Maqrizi’s &lt;em&gt;Ittiʿaz&lt;/em&gt; (left) and his &lt;em&gt;Muqaffa&lt;/em&gt; (right). (The text files are open in EditPad Pro with a training-data annotation schema applied to facilitate the easy identification of tags).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The corresponding alignments were then checked, inserting or removing tags where needed. A distinct pair of tags (@ALB@1@ and @ALE@1@) is used to easily demarcate a manually created tag from one generated by passim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When doing this type of evaluation, I am asking three questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Has passim entirely missed any cases of text reuse?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Has passim identified unrelated text as reuse?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Are the edges of the reuse correct – does the reuse start or end before or after the tags?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Figure 2 gives an example of parallel texts with manually evaluated alignments:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/old_posts/MB2-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Figure 2&lt;/strong&gt; A side-by-side view of corresponding alignment tags with manual correction in al-Maqrizi’s &lt;em&gt;Ittiʿaz&lt;/em&gt; (left) and his &lt;em&gt;Muqaffa&lt;/em&gt; (right).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-observations-human-vs-machine&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some observations: human vs. machine&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process of evaluating described above might sound particularly tedious and dull, but it is a valuable exercise for understanding both our texts and our methods. On the one hand, reading text reuse alignments so closely can teach us a lot about how authors copied, abridged and paraphrased from source texts. On the other, it teaches us the different strengths of humans and machines in identifying text reuse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The identification of text reuse is a task at which humans are actually quite poor. As I found in my own research, manual studies in text reuse are limited by two factors:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Memory: successfully identifying a case of reuse requires you to remember similarities in language and events.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Corpus size: comparing closely by hand can only be done on a relatively narrow corpus, and assembly of such a corpus will (like it or not) be subject to biases.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Passim does not suffer from these limitations: it can compare across an enormous corpus in a very short period of time (so there is no need to create a selective corpus or focus on a particular subject); it is not hindered by the limits of human memory; crucially, passim does not get tired or go cross-eyed after hours of closely scrutinising text. In other words, passim allows us to see text reuse at scale without being subject to the biases of text selection or the lack of precision caused by fatigue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When passim’s outputs were compared with those of my research, the results were very compelling: passim did not falsely identify passages of reuse, and it found nearly all of the instances of reuse I had found through close reading the texts. In addition, it did not find any meaningful instances of reuse that my own research had not identified. However, passim failed in instances where there was only a limited number of shared words between the texts and where shared words had been reordered. For example, where one work had omitted a long span of text or where lots of synonyms were used in the copy. Table 2 below shows an example of such a case:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Al-Maqrizi’s &lt;em&gt;Ittiʿaz&lt;/em&gt; (II: 197)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Al-Maqrizi’s &lt;em&gt;Muqaffa&lt;/em&gt; (III: 366-7)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;وكان من خبره أن &lt;u&gt;أباه&lt;/u&gt; على بن عبد الرحمن كانت &lt;u&gt;له&lt;/u&gt; &lt;u&gt;حال&lt;/u&gt; واسعة ببلد يعرف ب&lt;u&gt;يازور&lt;/u&gt;، &lt;u&gt;من ضياع فلسطين&lt;/u&gt;، وكان مقدّماً فيها؛ &lt;u&gt;فلما&lt;/u&gt; كبرت &lt;u&gt;حاله&lt;/u&gt; انتقل &lt;u&gt;إلى الرملة&lt;/u&gt; واستوطَنها، وصارت له وكلاء في الضياع. فاشْتُهِر هناك &lt;u&gt;وعرف&lt;/u&gt; بالعِفّة وال&lt;u&gt;صدق&lt;/u&gt; و&lt;u&gt;سماح&lt;/u&gt; &lt;u&gt;النفس&lt;/u&gt;، ف&lt;u&gt;رُدّ إليه&lt;/u&gt; &lt;u&gt;قضاء&lt;/u&gt; بعض &lt;u&gt;أعمال الرملة&lt;/u&gt;. &lt;u&gt;ونشأ له ابنان&lt;/u&gt; نجيبان، ولي أحدُهما الحكم بعد أبيه إلى أن توفي, ثم &lt;u&gt;خلفه أَخوه&lt;/u&gt; عبد الرحمن هذا من بعده، فعُرِف بسعة النفس وسعة الأخلاق،&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;كان &lt;u&gt;أبوه&lt;/u&gt; من أهل ضيعة &lt;u&gt;من ضياع فلسطين&lt;/u&gt; يقال لها “&lt;u&gt;يازور&lt;/u&gt;“، و&lt;u&gt;له&lt;/u&gt; بها &lt;u&gt;حال&lt;/u&gt; متّسعة ونباهة كبيرة. &lt;u&gt;فلما&lt;/u&gt; اتّسعَت &lt;u&gt;حاله&lt;/u&gt;، وكثر مالُه، أنِف من المقام بها وتحوّل &lt;u&gt;إلى الرملة&lt;/u&gt; وسكنها فشُهر بها. &lt;u&gt;وعُرف&lt;/u&gt; بال&lt;u&gt;صدق&lt;/u&gt; في القول و&lt;u&gt;سماح&lt;/u&gt;ة &lt;u&gt;النفس&lt;/u&gt;، فتقدّم الشهود بها، و&lt;u&gt;رُدّ إليه قضاءُ&lt;/u&gt; أكثر &lt;u&gt;أعمال الرملة&lt;/u&gt;. &lt;u&gt;ونشأ له ابنان&lt;/u&gt;، أصغرُهُما الحسن هذا. ف&lt;u&gt;خلف أخاه&lt;/u&gt;، القائمَ بعد أبيه، وأربى على أبيه وأخيه في حسن الطريقة وجميل السيرة وشرف الأعلاق&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Table 2&lt;/strong&gt;: A formatted version of alignment 41001 shown in figure 2 above. The underlining shows text reuse. For the human reader, it is clear from the subject matter and the patterns of similarity that al-Maqrīzī is copying from the same source text, but because the number of shared words is relatively small and the gaps between shared words large, passim was unable to align these two passages within its current parameters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These cases show an evident shortfall of passim when compared to manual study. Any researcher comparing the texts understands the content, and relies on this to find instances of text reuse. Where passim goes through the text and pairs up words and phrases irrespective of their meaning, the researcher often relies on the meaning of the text to find the instances of text reuse. Note, for example, in my own research I created a spreadsheet cross-referencing the events before proceeding to compare the texts. This means that researchers are not thrown off by the use of synonyms or when certain words are omitted but the overall meaning is retained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To an extent passim can be taught to recognise these marginal cases of text reuse. By creating a body of evaluation data, the alignment model will learn what kinds of patterns to associate with text reuse, including such marginal cases. This case study illustrates the importance of cooperation between Computer Scientists and Humanists for high-quality research in text reuse and book history. Without computational techniques, it is impossible to understand text reuse at scale and as a result our studies would remain narrow and at risk of bias. Yet, without subject-specialists, passim cannot learn what constitutes meaningful reuse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bibliography&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ibn Saʿd, &lt;em&gt;Kitab Tabaqat al-Kubra,&lt;/em&gt; 8, ed. Muhammad ʿAbd al-Qadir ʿAta, Beirut, 1990.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Al-Maqrizi, &lt;em&gt;Ittiʿaz al-Hunafa bi-Akhbar al-ʾImmah al-Fatimiyyin al-khulafa&lt;/em&gt;, 2, ed. Muhammad Hilmi Muhammad Ahmad, Cairo, 2008.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Al-Maqrizi, &lt;em&gt;Kitab al-Muqaffa al-Kabir&lt;/em&gt;, 3, ed. Muhạmmad al-Yaʿlawi, Beirut, 1987.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Al-Tabarī, &lt;em&gt;Taʾrikh al-Rusul wa-l-Muluk,&lt;/em&gt; 3, ed. Muhammad Abu al-Fadl Ibrahim, Cairo, 1990.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;For examples, see:&lt;a href=&quot;/2020/06-22.html&quot;&gt; Algorithmic Reading of Shiʿi Hadith Collections: Direct Borrowing and Common Sources&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/2019/12-03.html&quot;&gt;On Commentaries, Digressions, Transtextualities, and Rabbit Holes&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Mathew Barber</name></author><summary type="html">Text reuse is the term that we use to describe cases where one book shares verbatim material with another. Text reuse can be studied manually through the reading of texts in parallel, but it can also be detected computationally, using the passim algorithm. Computational approaches, which can compare thousands of books at once, can teach us many exciting things about Arabic book history that would be impossible through manual study. 1 In this blog, I would like to make some observations about passim’s outputs at the level of individual alignments (the paired passages produced by passim) rather than larger book relationships, and through them discuss how the human evaluation of passim’s outputs can improve the algorithm’s performance. A key point I would like to make here: passim is powerful, but it cannot understand the content of texts, sometimes leading it to identify cases of similarity between texts that do not constitute meaningful reuse. Identifying meaningful reuse In order to detect reuse, the passim algorithm makes a series of assumptions about what constitutes meaningful reuse. To give two key examples: The minimum number of words that need to be shared between two passages, for it to be considered a reuse case (the min-match parameter) The maximum length of a gap between the shared words in two passages, before it is either broken into two reuse cases, or not considered a reuse case (the gap parameter) If passim’s assumptions about the nature of meaningful reuse are incorrect, it will either output a large number of meaningless alignments, or it will miss cases of meaningful reuse. This is particularly an issue when passages contain similar names. Table 1 gives an example of the kind of alignments that are produced if the gap parameter is too long. Ibn Saʿd, Kitab Tabaqat al-Kubra (VIII: 91) Al-Tabarī, Taʾrikh al-Rusul wa-l-Muluk (III: 167) زينب بنت خزيمة بن الحارث بن عبد الله بن عمرو بن عبد مناف بن هلال بن عامر بن صعصعة وهي أم المساكين كانت تسمى بذلك في الجاهلية أخبرنا محمد بن عمر حدثنا محمد بن عبد الله عن الزهري قال كانت زينب بنت خزيمة الهلالية تدعى أم المساكين وكانت عند الطفيل بن الحارث بن المطلب وممن لم يذكر هشام في خبره هذا ممن روى عن رسول الله ص أنه تزوجه من النساء زينب بنت خزيمة وهي التي يقال لها أم المساكين من بني عامر بن صعصعة وهي زينب بنت خزيمة بن الحارث ابن عبد الله بن عمرو بن عبد مناف بن هلال بن عامر بن صعصعة وكانت قبل رسول الله عند الطفيل بن الحارث بن المطلب Table 1: In this alignment passim has matched a biographical entry for Zaynab bt. Khuzayma (a wife of the Prophet) from Ibn Saʿd’s Tabaqat with al-Tabari’s account of the Prophet’s marriage to Zaynab. You can see from the underlined words that passim has matched Zaynab’s full name, in addition to the phrase ‘ʿinda al-tifayli bin al-harithi bin al-mutallibi’. In addition, passim may have identified that both passages use Zaynab’s epithet ‘umm al-masakin’ (highlighted). Because a large gap has been allowed in the first passage between Zaynab’s full name and the final shared lines, the two matched passages are not meaningfully related. For any clear understanding of the nature of text reuse in our corpus, we must ensure that passim locates the maximum possible instances of text reuse, without falsely identifying instances such as in the example above. One solution is to computationally locate names of individuals within the texts  and then exclude those from passim’s analysis. This is currently being explored by Ryan Muther through the automatic detection of isnads (see further, Tracking Traditions: Identifying Isnads in the OpenITI Corpus). Additionally, it is important to establish a set of ground truths against which to evaluate passim’s performance and experiment with different parameters. This is done through the manual annotation of text reuse and/or correction of passim alignments. The process of creating evaluation data My research is concerned with identifying cases of text reuse in order to understand the survival of ‘lost’ Fatimid texts into the fifteenth century. For this research, I read through and closely compared texts that describe a 10-year period of Fatimid history. This led me to identify an instance of significant reuse between two texts by the famous Mamluk historian al-Maqrizi (d. 1442): the Ittiʿaz al-Hunafaʾ (a chronicle history of the Fatimids) and the kitab al-Muqaffa al-Kabir (a biographical dictionary). An exhaustive comparison of sections of these two works identified instances of text reuse, which could be used to evaluate passim’s performance. Passim was run on the chosen pair of books, and tags were inserted identifying where passim had located passages of reuse. These tags are in pairs, constituting a beginning and an end tag with a shared unique identifier (UI) number (e.g. @ALIGN@B@2@ and @ALIGN@E@2@). The UI number is specific to the passage as it is tagged in both books. Figure 1 gives an example of the tags in parallel texts: Figure 1 A side-by-side view of corresponding automatic alignment tags in al-Maqrizi’s Ittiʿaz (left) and his Muqaffa (right). (The text files are open in EditPad Pro with a training-data annotation schema applied to facilitate the easy identification of tags). The corresponding alignments were then checked, inserting or removing tags where needed. A distinct pair of tags (@ALB@1@ and @ALE@1@) is used to easily demarcate a manually created tag from one generated by passim. When doing this type of evaluation, I am asking three questions: Has passim entirely missed any cases of text reuse? Has passim identified unrelated text as reuse? Are the edges of the reuse correct – does the reuse start or end before or after the tags? Figure 2 gives an example of parallel texts with manually evaluated alignments: Figure 2 A side-by-side view of corresponding alignment tags with manual correction in al-Maqrizi’s Ittiʿaz (left) and his Muqaffa (right). Some observations: human vs. machine The process of evaluating described above might sound particularly tedious and dull, but it is a valuable exercise for understanding both our texts and our methods. On the one hand, reading text reuse alignments so closely can teach us a lot about how authors copied, abridged and paraphrased from source texts. On the other, it teaches us the different strengths of humans and machines in identifying text reuse. The identification of text reuse is a task at which humans are actually quite poor. As I found in my own research, manual studies in text reuse are limited by two factors: Memory: successfully identifying a case of reuse requires you to remember similarities in language and events. Corpus size: comparing closely by hand can only be done on a relatively narrow corpus, and assembly of such a corpus will (like it or not) be subject to biases. Passim does not suffer from these limitations: it can compare across an enormous corpus in a very short period of time (so there is no need to create a selective corpus or focus on a particular subject); it is not hindered by the limits of human memory; crucially, passim does not get tired or go cross-eyed after hours of closely scrutinising text. In other words, passim allows us to see text reuse at scale without being subject to the biases of text selection or the lack of precision caused by fatigue. When passim’s outputs were compared with those of my research, the results were very compelling: passim did not falsely identify passages of reuse, and it found nearly all of the instances of reuse I had found through close reading the texts. In addition, it did not find any meaningful instances of reuse that my own research had not identified. However, passim failed in instances where there was only a limited number of shared words between the texts and where shared words had been reordered. For example, where one work had omitted a long span of text or where lots of synonyms were used in the copy. Table 2 below shows an example of such a case: Al-Maqrizi’s Ittiʿaz (II: 197) Al-Maqrizi’s Muqaffa (III: 366-7) وكان من خبره أن أباه على بن عبد الرحمن كانت له حال واسعة ببلد يعرف بيازور، من ضياع فلسطين، وكان مقدّماً فيها؛ فلما كبرت حاله انتقل إلى الرملة واستوطَنها، وصارت له وكلاء في الضياع. فاشْتُهِر هناك وعرف بالعِفّة والصدق وسماح النفس، فرُدّ إليه قضاء بعض أعمال الرملة. ونشأ له ابنان نجيبان، ولي أحدُهما الحكم بعد أبيه إلى أن توفي, ثم خلفه أَخوه عبد الرحمن هذا من بعده، فعُرِف بسعة النفس وسعة الأخلاق، كان أبوه من أهل ضيعة من ضياع فلسطين يقال لها “يازور“، وله بها حال متّسعة ونباهة كبيرة. فلما اتّسعَت حاله، وكثر مالُه، أنِف من المقام بها وتحوّل إلى الرملة وسكنها فشُهر بها. وعُرف بالصدق في القول وسماحة النفس، فتقدّم الشهود بها، ورُدّ إليه قضاءُ أكثر أعمال الرملة. ونشأ له ابنان، أصغرُهُما الحسن هذا. فخلف أخاه، القائمَ بعد أبيه، وأربى على أبيه وأخيه في حسن الطريقة وجميل السيرة وشرف الأعلاق Table 2: A formatted version of alignment 41001 shown in figure 2 above. The underlining shows text reuse. For the human reader, it is clear from the subject matter and the patterns of similarity that al-Maqrīzī is copying from the same source text, but because the number of shared words is relatively small and the gaps between shared words large, passim was unable to align these two passages within its current parameters. These cases show an evident shortfall of passim when compared to manual study. Any researcher comparing the texts understands the content, and relies on this to find instances of text reuse. Where passim goes through the text and pairs up words and phrases irrespective of their meaning, the researcher often relies on the meaning of the text to find the instances of text reuse. Note, for example, in my own research I created a spreadsheet cross-referencing the events before proceeding to compare the texts. This means that researchers are not thrown off by the use of synonyms or when certain words are omitted but the overall meaning is retained. To an extent passim can be taught to recognise these marginal cases of text reuse. By creating a body of evaluation data, the alignment model will learn what kinds of patterns to associate with text reuse, including such marginal cases. This case study illustrates the importance of cooperation between Computer Scientists and Humanists for high-quality research in text reuse and book history. Without computational techniques, it is impossible to understand text reuse at scale and as a result our studies would remain narrow and at risk of bias. Yet, without subject-specialists, passim cannot learn what constitutes meaningful reuse.   Bibliography Ibn Saʿd, Kitab Tabaqat al-Kubra, 8, ed. Muhammad ʿAbd al-Qadir ʿAta, Beirut, 1990. Al-Maqrizi, Ittiʿaz al-Hunafa bi-Akhbar al-ʾImmah al-Fatimiyyin al-khulafa, 2, ed. Muhammad Hilmi Muhammad Ahmad, Cairo, 2008. Al-Maqrizi, Kitab al-Muqaffa al-Kabir, 3, ed. Muhạmmad al-Yaʿlawi, Beirut, 1987. Al-Tabarī, Taʾrikh al-Rusul wa-l-Muluk, 3, ed. Muhammad Abu al-Fadl Ibrahim, Cairo, 1990. For examples, see: Algorithmic Reading of Shiʿi Hadith Collections: Direct Borrowing and Common Sources and On Commentaries, Digressions, Transtextualities, and Rabbit Holes &amp;#8617;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Preserving Pre-Modern Terminologies</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/08-05.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Preserving Pre-Modern Terminologies" /><published>2020-08-05T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-08-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/Preserving%20Pre-Modern%20Terminologies</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/08-05.html">&lt;p&gt;To categorise things is a fundamental human and scholarly instinct and activity. And yet it is one not without obstacles, for we soon learn that the world is more complex than we originally thought or that we are confronted with something which refuses to conform to our usual categories. To put it somewhat casually, if our world is populated only by monochrome horses, we probably will have a hard time putting zebras into our usual colour categories—until we make room for them in our classification system. (Of course, even if we fail to do so, this would still allow us to pat them on the head and full-heartedly embrace their difference.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this blog, I suggest that similar problems occasionally occur when we try to classify pre-modern Islamicate texts in our OpenITI / KITAB corpus respectively when we try to fit certain pieces of information related to them into our existing metadata categories. Many of these texts were produced within intellectual fields with their own distinctive terminologies and practices which more often use terms and refer to activities without equivalent in our contemporary world. This effectively means that our usual categories are on occasion unable to catch differences for which they were not made. (Some more or less extensive periods of head-patting might be necessary here.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, of course, we might simply call a zebra a black horse and ignore the white stripes, but considering the loss of information that this would entail, it is probably not such a good idea. At KITAB, we are convinced that our metadata should, as far as possible, preserve the terminology of our pre-modern authors and respect distinctions and specificities which they felt were important enough to be reflected in language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give a small, but illustrative example. In the OpenITI / KITAB corpus, the term &lt;em&gt;takhrij&lt;/em&gt; often occurs in the context of &lt;em&gt;mashyakhat&lt;/em&gt; (sg. &lt;em&gt;mashyakha&lt;/em&gt;) “lists of shaykhs of an individual” in the sense that a particular &lt;em&gt;mashyakha&lt;/em&gt; is stated to be the “&lt;em&gt;mashyakha&lt;/em&gt; of X, &lt;em&gt;takhrij&lt;/em&gt; Y.” For example, our corpus contains the &lt;em&gt;mashyakha&lt;/em&gt; of Muhammad b. Ibrahim al-Bayani in the &lt;em&gt;takhrij&lt;/em&gt; of Ibn Rafiʿ al-Sallami. This means that Ibn Rafiʿ al-Sallami contributed to the creation of the &lt;em&gt;mashyakha&lt;/em&gt; of al-Bayani through an activity called &lt;em&gt;takhrij&lt;/em&gt; (see below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/old_posts/LZB-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although there is variation with regard to their individual make-up, a &lt;em&gt;mashyakha&lt;/em&gt; generally is a form of text which mentions the shaykhs of an individual and for each of the shaykhs mentioned adduces one or more hadiths that were transmitted by him or her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such lists of shaykhs may also be termed &lt;em&gt;muʿjam&lt;/em&gt; (pl. &lt;em&gt;maʿajim&lt;/em&gt;). A &lt;em&gt;muʿjam&lt;/em&gt; essentially is the same thing as a &lt;em&gt;mashyakha&lt;/em&gt;, with the difference that it mostly arranges the shaykhs in alphabetical order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To a modern reader, this might seem like a strange form of text, but such texts fulfilled clear purposes within the field of knowledge transmission and especially hadith transmission. They showed the position of an individual within the field and allowed to see in condensed form under which scholars that individual had studied and which transmissive chains he therefore “owned.” But they also allowed the students of that individual to connect with the same transmissive chains in a structured and efficient way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what about this term &lt;em&gt;takhrij&lt;/em&gt;? To what sort of text and associated practices does it refer  and how can we account for its specificities in our metadata?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grammatically speaking, &lt;em&gt;takhrij&lt;/em&gt; is the verbal noun of the verb &lt;em&gt;kharraja / yukharriju&lt;/em&gt; “to extract.” In the pre-modern scholarly social worlds, in which the term was used in this particular sense, it clearly refers to a distinct form of scholarly activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what exactly is this activity? While it is not easy to pin down the exact nature, it seems to have been of an essentially compilationary character. It furthermore was something one could do for oneself (“&lt;em&gt;kharraja li-nafsihi…&lt;/em&gt;.”) or for someone else (&lt;em&gt;“kharraja lahu&lt;/em&gt;…”). There is a record of siblings who engaged in this activity for each other, fathers for their sons, students for their shaykhs, scholarly peers for each other, to name but a few examples. The individual actively engaging in the activity of &lt;em&gt;takhrij&lt;/em&gt; is referred to as &lt;em&gt;mukharrij,&lt;/em&gt; whereas the one for whom someone else engages in this activity is termed &lt;em&gt;mukharraj lahu.&lt;/em&gt; It seems that some individuals specialised in this form of activity more so than others (introduction to Subki’s &lt;em&gt;Muʿjam&lt;/em&gt;, pp. 15–16). The aforementioned Ibn Rafiʿ al-Sallami is a good example. He is credited with the &lt;em&gt;takhrij&lt;/em&gt; of more than a dozen &lt;em&gt;mashyakhat&lt;/em&gt; for others (Bayani &lt;em&gt;Mashyakha&lt;/em&gt;, pp. 20–21).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on the structure and content of the individual &lt;em&gt;mashaykha&lt;/em&gt; “list of shaykhs,” the work involved in its creation must have been a more or less labour-intensive combination of several tasks. The first task involved gathering hadith material transmitted by the individual shaykhs and the respective transmissive chains by going through one’s own or someone else’s notes, audience certificates, and &lt;em&gt;ijazat&lt;/em&gt; “authorisations to transmit a text” (for example, Abu ʿAbdallah Muhammad al-Razi refers to Abu Tahir al-Silafi as the “&lt;em&gt;mukharrij hadhihi l-fawaʾid min masmuʿati,”&lt;/em&gt; Razi &lt;em&gt;Mashyakha&lt;/em&gt;, p. 100), making a selection of the gathered material, maybe putting the shaykhs into alphabetical order, maybe adding biographical information for each of them, and so forth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This essentially compilationary character of the activity is corroborated by other verbs that are used instead of &lt;em&gt;kharraja&lt;/em&gt;. Apart from the more neutral verb &lt;em&gt;ʿamila&lt;/em&gt; “to make,” most notably, the verb &lt;em&gt;jamaʿa&lt;/em&gt; “to gather” occurs. For example, al-Samʿani states that he had put together a &lt;em&gt;muʿjam&lt;/em&gt; for his son (&lt;em&gt;“qad kuntu jamaʿtu muʿjam shuyukhihi”&lt;/em&gt;) (Samʿani &lt;em&gt;Muntakhab&lt;/em&gt;, p. 112). Al-Dhahabi refers to this piece of information with the phrase “his father produced a &lt;em&gt;muʿjam&lt;/em&gt; for him” (&lt;em&gt;“ʿamila lahu abuhu muʿjaman”&lt;/em&gt;) (Dhahabi &lt;em&gt;Siyar aʿlam al-nubalaʾ&lt;/em&gt;, vol. 22, p. 107).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is interesting to note that some form of &lt;em&gt;personal relationship&lt;/em&gt; mostly seems to be playing a role when people engaged in this activity for someone else. As has already been pointed out, they put together &lt;em&gt;mashyakhat / maʿajim&lt;/em&gt; for their kin (even milk kinship, see Ibn al-ʿAttar &lt;em&gt;Tuhfat al-talibin&lt;/em&gt;, p. 28), teachers, and peers. Even if someone apparently had to be talked into doing the work, the personal relationship seems to matter. An example for the latter case is provided by the introduction to Burhan al-Din al-Jaʿbari’s &lt;em&gt;Mashyakha al-shamiyya&lt;/em&gt;, which was put together by al-Qasim b. Muhammad al-Birzali (i.e., al-Birzali was the &lt;em&gt;mukharrij&lt;/em&gt;). Al-Birzali recalls the following in the opening passage of the &lt;em&gt;mashyakha&lt;/em&gt;: “He [i.e., Burhan al-Din] had a &lt;em&gt;mashyakha&lt;/em&gt; that contained all his shaykhs from Baghdad from whom he transmitted hadith and which had been put together for him by Jamal al-Din al-Qalanisi and which hadith students and those who wanted to transmit hadith (&lt;em&gt;ṭalabat al-hadith wa-l-raghibuna fi l-riwaya&lt;/em&gt;) read in his presence […]. Then he wanted that another &lt;em&gt;mashyakha&lt;/em&gt; be put together for him (&lt;em&gt;yukharraj lahu&lt;/em&gt;) which would contain all his shaykhs from Syria so that the material transmitted by him and his shaykhs would be more numerous and his students and all those who sought him out, traveled to him, and visited him would benefit from that. He wrote to me in that regard and sent a companion of his who prodded me (&lt;em&gt;yuharriduni&lt;/em&gt;) into putting together the respective material (&lt;em&gt;jamʿ al-matlub&lt;/em&gt;).” (MS Leipzig Vollers 719-01, 2v–3r).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above quote also well illustrates one purpose of the &lt;em&gt;mashyakhat:&lt;/em&gt; They allowed to see how each of the shaykhs mentioned in them connected the individual whose &lt;em&gt;mashyakha&lt;/em&gt; it was (the so-called &lt;em&gt;“sahib al-mashyakha”&lt;/em&gt;) to transmissive chains that lead all the way up to the Prophet and that were needed for the legitimate transmission of knowledge. By virtue of the same logic, if the students of the &lt;em&gt;sahib al-mashyakha&lt;/em&gt; read the &lt;em&gt;mashyakha&lt;/em&gt; in his presence&lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; they were connected to all of his chains of transmission in a highly efficient and organised way (among other motivations that might play a role, this explains the interest in large numbers expressed in the above quote).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if a &lt;em&gt;mukharrij&lt;/em&gt; put together a &lt;em&gt;mashyakha&lt;/em&gt; for someone else, what was the respective contribution of &lt;em&gt;mukharrij&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;mukharraj lahu&lt;/em&gt;? Who should be considered the “author”? Both? Only the &lt;em&gt;mukharrij&lt;/em&gt;? In the latter case, are we not missing something important in our metadata? And is “author” even a good term to describe this sort of activity?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question of what the &lt;em&gt;mukharrij&lt;/em&gt; actually did is not necessarily easy to answer. It is rather fascinating to see how often it puzzles the modern editors of &lt;em&gt;mashyakhat&lt;/em&gt; who occasionally state they do not know: “As far as the work of the &lt;em&gt;mukharrij&lt;/em&gt; is concerned, we have no information that would clarify what his work actually consisted in” (Naʿʿal &lt;em&gt;Mashyakha&lt;/em&gt;, p. 22; for a similar statement, see Subki &lt;em&gt;Muʿjam&lt;/em&gt;, p. 6). As the editor of Subki’s &lt;em&gt;Muʿjam&lt;/em&gt; suggests, things are even more complicated insofar as the fact that passages are written in the first person singular does not necessarily mean they were really written by that person. He highlights a passage by al-Dhahabi in which al-Dhahabi writes about the &lt;em&gt;Muʿjam&lt;/em&gt; of al-Samʿani’s son ʿAbd al-Rahim that it is “his father’s words put in the mouth of ʿAbd al-Rahim” (&lt;em&gt;“wa-huwa kalam abihi ʿala lisan ʿAbd al-Rahim”&lt;/em&gt;) (see Subki &lt;em&gt;Muʿjam&lt;/em&gt;, p. 6; for the quote, see Dhahabi &lt;em&gt;Tarikh al-islam&lt;/em&gt;, vol. 12, p. 58).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give another example of how difficult it is to determine who did what, in the &lt;em&gt;mashyakha&lt;/em&gt; of Muhammad b. al-Anjab al-Naʿʿal, the &lt;em&gt;takhrij&lt;/em&gt; of which is attributed to al-Mundhiri. This much is stated by al-Naʿʿal. He writes: “Thus I asked God for guidance and put together in this book a large number of the shaykhs that had issued an &lt;em&gt;ijaza&lt;/em&gt; to me” (&lt;em&gt;“wa-kharrajtu fi hadha l-kitab jumla min mashayikhi al-mujizin;”&lt;/em&gt; see Naʿʿal &lt;em&gt;Mashyakha&lt;/em&gt;, p. 55). So, al-Naʿʿal refers—in the literal sense of the sentence—to himself as engaged in &lt;em&gt;takhrij&lt;/em&gt;. If so, what role was left to al-Mundhiri, who is explicitly named as the &lt;em&gt;mukharrij&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not the appropriate place for an extensive study of the practice of &lt;em&gt;takhrij&lt;/em&gt;. What matters here is that from the perspective of corpus management it would be absurd to build a corpus consisting specifically of Islamicate texts, yet at the same time disregard culturally specific scholarly practices which &lt;em&gt;generate what are unique items of metadata for us&lt;/em&gt;. Unless we make use of such terms, we will be turning zebras into black horses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To an extent, this is what happens in contemporary library catalogues. Thus, with regard to &lt;em&gt;takhrij&lt;/em&gt; and the distinction in the pre-modern sources between &lt;em&gt;mukharrij&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;mukharraj lahu,&lt;/em&gt; the catalogues characteristically cannot really and fully accommodate the situation created by the pre-modern scholarly practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may be demonstrated by the two worldcat entries for al-Bayani’s above-mentioned &lt;em&gt;mashyakha&lt;/em&gt;. In one entry, the work is attributed to Ibn Rafiʿ al-Sallami (i.e., the &lt;em&gt;mukharrij&lt;/em&gt;); in the other entry, it is attributed to al-Bayani (=Ibn Imam al-Sakhra) (i.e., the &lt;em&gt;mukharraj lahu&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/old_posts/LZB-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At KITAB, we are convinced that such information must be recorded in our metadata in a &lt;em&gt;consistent and machine-readable way.&lt;/em&gt; If our sources tell us &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; someone acted as a &lt;em&gt;mukharrij&lt;/em&gt; for someone, we should &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; be able to retrieve both &lt;em&gt;mukharrij&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;mukharraj lahu&lt;/em&gt;, —as well as the fact that they are linked through this particular relationship. We are convinced that being able to search our corpus metadata for information of this kind constitutes real progress book history and we are currently working out a system of how to &lt;em&gt;generally&lt;/em&gt; preserve the pre-modern terminology we find in our texts and the various relations between texts and persons signified by terms such as &lt;em&gt;takhrij&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;mukharrij,&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;mukharrij lahu&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, it is not &lt;em&gt;entirely&lt;/em&gt; wrong to state that the &lt;em&gt;mukharrij&lt;/em&gt; is the “author,” but it is not entirely right either. Most certainly, such terms force us to be more specific with regard to our notion of authorship, make room for pre-modern terminology, and rethink what they meant in the highly specific historical scholarly worlds we are dealing with and in which the terms arise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the perspective of corpus management, we must be ready to adapt our metadata categories to accommodate specificities if we become aware of them through research. If we level them, our metadata is much poorer than it has to be. By contrast, preserving them along with the pre-modern terminologies themselves will lay the foundations for retrieving richer information from our corpus and will allow users to ask different questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While none of this can be implemented overnight, it is important to recognise the issue and begin to address it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bibliography&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;al-Bayani, Muhammad b. Ibrahim: &lt;em&gt;Mashyakhat al-musnid Muhammad b. Ibrahim al-Bayani al-maʿruf bi-Ibn Imam al-Sakhra.&lt;/em&gt; Takhrij al-hafiz Ibn Rafiʿ al-Sallami. Bayrut 2004&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;al-Dhahabi, Shams al-Din Abu ʿAbd Allah Muhammad b. Ahmad: &lt;em&gt;Tarikh al-islam.&lt;/em&gt; Bayrut 2003&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;al-Jaʿbari, Burhan ad-Din Abu Ishaq Ibrahim b. ʿUmar  b. Ibrahim b. Khalil al-Rabaʿi: &lt;em&gt;Mashyakha mubaraka Shamiyya li-l-shaykh al-imam al-ʿalim al-ʽamil Burhan ad-Din Abu Ishaq Ibrahim b. ʿUmar  b. Ibrahim b. Khalil al-Rabaʿi al-Jaʿbari al-Shafiʿi nazil balad al-Khalil ʿalaihi al-salam ʿan shuyukhihi al-shamiyyin alladhina ajazu lahu.&lt;/em&gt; Takhrij al-Qasim b. Muhammad b. Yusuf b. Muhammad al-Birzali. MS Leipzig Vollers 719-01&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.refaiya.uni-leipzig.de/servlets/solr/select?q=%2BobjectType%3A%22islamhs%22+-mymss_ihsstatus%3A%22STAT0001%22+%2B%28allMeta%3A%D9%85%D8%B4%D9%8A%D8%AE%D8%A9+mymss_allmeta_diacr%3A%D9%85%D8%B4%D9%8A%D8%AE%D8%A9%29&amp;amp;XSL.lastPage.SESSION=%2Fsearch_form_islamhs_advanced.xed&amp;amp;fl=id%2CreturnId%2CobjectType&amp;amp;sort=mymss_ihsinvent+asc&amp;amp;version=4.5&amp;amp;mask=search_form_islamhs_advanced.xed&amp;amp;start=0&amp;amp;fl=id,returnId&amp;amp;rows=1&amp;amp;XSL.Style=browse&amp;amp;origrows=25&quot;&gt;https://www.refaiya.uni-leipzig.de/servlets/solr/select?q=%2BobjectType%3A%22islamhs%22+-mymss_ihsstatus%3A%22STAT0001%22+%2B%28allMeta%3A%D9%85%D8%B4%D9%8A%D8%AE%D8%A9+mymss_allmeta_diacr%3A%D9%85%D8%B4%D9%8A%D8%AE%D8%A9%29&amp;amp;XSL.lastPage.SESSION=%2Fsearch_form_islamhs_advanced.xed&amp;amp;fl=id%2CreturnId%2CobjectType&amp;amp;sort=mymss_ihsinvent+asc&amp;amp;version=4.5&amp;amp;mask=search_form_islamhs_advanced.xed&amp;amp;start=0&amp;amp;fl=id,returnId&amp;amp;rows=1&amp;amp;XSL.Style=browse&amp;amp;origrows=25&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;al-Naʿʿal, Saʾin al-Din Muhammad b. al-Anjab: &lt;em&gt;Mashyakhat al-Naʿʿal al-Baghdadi.&lt;/em&gt; Takhrij al-hafiz Rashid al-Din Muhammad b. ʿAbd al-ʿAzim  al-Mundhiri&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; Baghdad 1975&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;al-Nawawi: &lt;em&gt;Al-Ijaz fi sharh sunan Abi Dawud al-Sijistani. wa-fi muqaddimat tahqiqihi Tuhfat al-talibin fi tarjamat al-imam Muhyi al-Din tasnif ʿAlaʾ al-Din ʿAli b. Ibrahim b. al-ʿAttar.&lt;/em&gt; ʿAmman 2007&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;al-Razi, Abu ʿAbd Allah Muhammad b. Ahmad b. Ibrahim: &lt;em&gt;Mashyakhat al-shaykh al-ajall Abi ʿAbd Allah Muhammad b. Ahmad b. Ibrahim al-Razi al-maʿruf bi-Ibn al-Hattab wa-thabat masmuʿatihi bi-intiqaʾ al-shaykh al-ajall al-imam al-ʿalim al-hafiz Abi Tahir Ahmad b. Muhammad b. Ahmad al-Silafi.&lt;/em&gt; Al-Riyad 1994&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;al-Samʿani, Abu Saʿd ʿAbd al-Karim b. Muhammad b. Mansur al-Tamimi: Al-&lt;em&gt;Muntakhab min muʿjam shuyukh al-imam al-hafiz Abi Saʿd ʿAbd al-Karim b. Muhammad b. Mansur al-Samʿani al-Tamimi.&lt;/em&gt; Al-Riyad 1996&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;al-Subki, Taj al-Din ʿAbd al-Wahhab b. ʿAli: &lt;em&gt;Muʿjam al-shuyukh.&lt;/em&gt; Takhrij Shams al-Din al-Salihi. Bayrut 2004&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Lorenz Nigst</name></author><summary type="html">To categorise things is a fundamental human and scholarly instinct and activity. And yet it is one not without obstacles, for we soon learn that the world is more complex than we originally thought or that we are confronted with something which refuses to conform to our usual categories. To put it somewhat casually, if our world is populated only by monochrome horses, we probably will have a hard time putting zebras into our usual colour categories—until we make room for them in our classification system. (Of course, even if we fail to do so, this would still allow us to pat them on the head and full-heartedly embrace their difference.) In this blog, I suggest that similar problems occasionally occur when we try to classify pre-modern Islamicate texts in our OpenITI / KITAB corpus respectively when we try to fit certain pieces of information related to them into our existing metadata categories. Many of these texts were produced within intellectual fields with their own distinctive terminologies and practices which more often use terms and refer to activities without equivalent in our contemporary world. This effectively means that our usual categories are on occasion unable to catch differences for which they were not made. (Some more or less extensive periods of head-patting might be necessary here.) Now, of course, we might simply call a zebra a black horse and ignore the white stripes, but considering the loss of information that this would entail, it is probably not such a good idea. At KITAB, we are convinced that our metadata should, as far as possible, preserve the terminology of our pre-modern authors and respect distinctions and specificities which they felt were important enough to be reflected in language. To give a small, but illustrative example. In the OpenITI / KITAB corpus, the term takhrij often occurs in the context of mashyakhat (sg. mashyakha) “lists of shaykhs of an individual” in the sense that a particular mashyakha is stated to be the “mashyakha of X, takhrij Y.” For example, our corpus contains the mashyakha of Muhammad b. Ibrahim al-Bayani in the takhrij of Ibn Rafiʿ al-Sallami. This means that Ibn Rafiʿ al-Sallami contributed to the creation of the mashyakha of al-Bayani through an activity called takhrij (see below). Although there is variation with regard to their individual make-up, a mashyakha generally is a form of text which mentions the shaykhs of an individual and for each of the shaykhs mentioned adduces one or more hadiths that were transmitted by him or her. Such lists of shaykhs may also be termed muʿjam (pl. maʿajim). A muʿjam essentially is the same thing as a mashyakha, with the difference that it mostly arranges the shaykhs in alphabetical order. To a modern reader, this might seem like a strange form of text, but such texts fulfilled clear purposes within the field of knowledge transmission and especially hadith transmission. They showed the position of an individual within the field and allowed to see in condensed form under which scholars that individual had studied and which transmissive chains he therefore “owned.” But they also allowed the students of that individual to connect with the same transmissive chains in a structured and efficient way. But what about this term takhrij? To what sort of text and associated practices does it refer  and how can we account for its specificities in our metadata? Grammatically speaking, takhrij is the verbal noun of the verb kharraja / yukharriju “to extract.” In the pre-modern scholarly social worlds, in which the term was used in this particular sense, it clearly refers to a distinct form of scholarly activity. But what exactly is this activity? While it is not easy to pin down the exact nature, it seems to have been of an essentially compilationary character. It furthermore was something one could do for oneself (“kharraja li-nafsihi….”) or for someone else (“kharraja lahu…”). There is a record of siblings who engaged in this activity for each other, fathers for their sons, students for their shaykhs, scholarly peers for each other, to name but a few examples. The individual actively engaging in the activity of takhrij is referred to as mukharrij, whereas the one for whom someone else engages in this activity is termed mukharraj lahu. It seems that some individuals specialised in this form of activity more so than others (introduction to Subki’s Muʿjam, pp. 15–16). The aforementioned Ibn Rafiʿ al-Sallami is a good example. He is credited with the takhrij of more than a dozen mashyakhat for others (Bayani Mashyakha, pp. 20–21). Depending on the structure and content of the individual mashaykha “list of shaykhs,” the work involved in its creation must have been a more or less labour-intensive combination of several tasks. The first task involved gathering hadith material transmitted by the individual shaykhs and the respective transmissive chains by going through one’s own or someone else’s notes, audience certificates, and ijazat “authorisations to transmit a text” (for example, Abu ʿAbdallah Muhammad al-Razi refers to Abu Tahir al-Silafi as the “mukharrij hadhihi l-fawaʾid min masmuʿati,” Razi Mashyakha, p. 100), making a selection of the gathered material, maybe putting the shaykhs into alphabetical order, maybe adding biographical information for each of them, and so forth. This essentially compilationary character of the activity is corroborated by other verbs that are used instead of kharraja. Apart from the more neutral verb ʿamila “to make,” most notably, the verb jamaʿa “to gather” occurs. For example, al-Samʿani states that he had put together a muʿjam for his son (“qad kuntu jamaʿtu muʿjam shuyukhihi”) (Samʿani Muntakhab, p. 112). Al-Dhahabi refers to this piece of information with the phrase “his father produced a muʿjam for him” (“ʿamila lahu abuhu muʿjaman”) (Dhahabi Siyar aʿlam al-nubalaʾ, vol. 22, p. 107). It is interesting to note that some form of personal relationship mostly seems to be playing a role when people engaged in this activity for someone else. As has already been pointed out, they put together mashyakhat / maʿajim for their kin (even milk kinship, see Ibn al-ʿAttar Tuhfat al-talibin, p. 28), teachers, and peers. Even if someone apparently had to be talked into doing the work, the personal relationship seems to matter. An example for the latter case is provided by the introduction to Burhan al-Din al-Jaʿbari’s Mashyakha al-shamiyya, which was put together by al-Qasim b. Muhammad al-Birzali (i.e., al-Birzali was the mukharrij). Al-Birzali recalls the following in the opening passage of the mashyakha: “He [i.e., Burhan al-Din] had a mashyakha that contained all his shaykhs from Baghdad from whom he transmitted hadith and which had been put together for him by Jamal al-Din al-Qalanisi and which hadith students and those who wanted to transmit hadith (ṭalabat al-hadith wa-l-raghibuna fi l-riwaya) read in his presence […]. Then he wanted that another mashyakha be put together for him (yukharraj lahu) which would contain all his shaykhs from Syria so that the material transmitted by him and his shaykhs would be more numerous and his students and all those who sought him out, traveled to him, and visited him would benefit from that. He wrote to me in that regard and sent a companion of his who prodded me (yuharriduni) into putting together the respective material (jamʿ al-matlub).” (MS Leipzig Vollers 719-01, 2v–3r). The above quote also well illustrates one purpose of the mashyakhat: They allowed to see how each of the shaykhs mentioned in them connected the individual whose mashyakha it was (the so-called “sahib al-mashyakha”) to transmissive chains that lead all the way up to the Prophet and that were needed for the legitimate transmission of knowledge. By virtue of the same logic, if the students of the sahib al-mashyakha read the mashyakha in his presence, they were connected to all of his chains of transmission in a highly efficient and organised way (among other motivations that might play a role, this explains the interest in large numbers expressed in the above quote). But if a mukharrij put together a mashyakha for someone else, what was the respective contribution of mukharrij and mukharraj lahu? Who should be considered the “author”? Both? Only the mukharrij? In the latter case, are we not missing something important in our metadata? And is “author” even a good term to describe this sort of activity? The question of what the mukharrij actually did is not necessarily easy to answer. It is rather fascinating to see how often it puzzles the modern editors of mashyakhat who occasionally state they do not know: “As far as the work of the mukharrij is concerned, we have no information that would clarify what his work actually consisted in” (Naʿʿal Mashyakha, p. 22; for a similar statement, see Subki Muʿjam, p. 6). As the editor of Subki’s Muʿjam suggests, things are even more complicated insofar as the fact that passages are written in the first person singular does not necessarily mean they were really written by that person. He highlights a passage by al-Dhahabi in which al-Dhahabi writes about the Muʿjam of al-Samʿani’s son ʿAbd al-Rahim that it is “his father’s words put in the mouth of ʿAbd al-Rahim” (“wa-huwa kalam abihi ʿala lisan ʿAbd al-Rahim”) (see Subki Muʿjam, p. 6; for the quote, see Dhahabi Tarikh al-islam, vol. 12, p. 58). To give another example of how difficult it is to determine who did what, in the mashyakha of Muhammad b. al-Anjab al-Naʿʿal, the takhrij of which is attributed to al-Mundhiri. This much is stated by al-Naʿʿal. He writes: “Thus I asked God for guidance and put together in this book a large number of the shaykhs that had issued an ijaza to me” (“wa-kharrajtu fi hadha l-kitab jumla min mashayikhi al-mujizin;” see Naʿʿal Mashyakha, p. 55). So, al-Naʿʿal refers—in the literal sense of the sentence—to himself as engaged in takhrij. If so, what role was left to al-Mundhiri, who is explicitly named as the mukharrij? This is not the appropriate place for an extensive study of the practice of takhrij. What matters here is that from the perspective of corpus management it would be absurd to build a corpus consisting specifically of Islamicate texts, yet at the same time disregard culturally specific scholarly practices which generate what are unique items of metadata for us. Unless we make use of such terms, we will be turning zebras into black horses. To an extent, this is what happens in contemporary library catalogues. Thus, with regard to takhrij and the distinction in the pre-modern sources between mukharrij and mukharraj lahu, the catalogues characteristically cannot really and fully accommodate the situation created by the pre-modern scholarly practices. This may be demonstrated by the two worldcat entries for al-Bayani’s above-mentioned mashyakha. In one entry, the work is attributed to Ibn Rafiʿ al-Sallami (i.e., the mukharrij); in the other entry, it is attributed to al-Bayani (=Ibn Imam al-Sakhra) (i.e., the mukharraj lahu). At KITAB, we are convinced that such information must be recorded in our metadata in a consistent and machine-readable way. If our sources tell us that someone acted as a mukharrij for someone, we should always be able to retrieve both mukharrij and mukharraj lahu, —as well as the fact that they are linked through this particular relationship. We are convinced that being able to search our corpus metadata for information of this kind constitutes real progress book history and we are currently working out a system of how to generally preserve the pre-modern terminology we find in our texts and the various relations between texts and persons signified by terms such as takhrij, mukharrij, and mukharrij lahu. Of course, it is not entirely wrong to state that the mukharrij is the “author,” but it is not entirely right either. Most certainly, such terms force us to be more specific with regard to our notion of authorship, make room for pre-modern terminology, and rethink what they meant in the highly specific historical scholarly worlds we are dealing with and in which the terms arise. From the perspective of corpus management, we must be ready to adapt our metadata categories to accommodate specificities if we become aware of them through research. If we level them, our metadata is much poorer than it has to be. By contrast, preserving them along with the pre-modern terminologies themselves will lay the foundations for retrieving richer information from our corpus and will allow users to ask different questions. While none of this can be implemented overnight, it is important to recognise the issue and begin to address it. Bibliography al-Bayani, Muhammad b. Ibrahim: Mashyakhat al-musnid Muhammad b. Ibrahim al-Bayani al-maʿruf bi-Ibn Imam al-Sakhra. Takhrij al-hafiz Ibn Rafiʿ al-Sallami. Bayrut 2004 al-Dhahabi, Shams al-Din Abu ʿAbd Allah Muhammad b. Ahmad: Tarikh al-islam. Bayrut 2003 al-Jaʿbari, Burhan ad-Din Abu Ishaq Ibrahim b. ʿUmar  b. Ibrahim b. Khalil al-Rabaʿi: Mashyakha mubaraka Shamiyya li-l-shaykh al-imam al-ʿalim al-ʽamil Burhan ad-Din Abu Ishaq Ibrahim b. ʿUmar  b. Ibrahim b. Khalil al-Rabaʿi al-Jaʿbari al-Shafiʿi nazil balad al-Khalil ʿalaihi al-salam ʿan shuyukhihi al-shamiyyin alladhina ajazu lahu. Takhrij al-Qasim b. Muhammad b. Yusuf b. Muhammad al-Birzali. MS Leipzig Vollers 719-01 https://www.refaiya.uni-leipzig.de/servlets/solr/select?q=%2BobjectType%3A%22islamhs%22+-mymss_ihsstatus%3A%22STAT0001%22+%2B%28allMeta%3A%D9%85%D8%B4%D9%8A%D8%AE%D8%A9+mymss_allmeta_diacr%3A%D9%85%D8%B4%D9%8A%D8%AE%D8%A9%29&amp;amp;XSL.lastPage.SESSION=%2Fsearch_form_islamhs_advanced.xed&amp;amp;fl=id%2CreturnId%2CobjectType&amp;amp;sort=mymss_ihsinvent+asc&amp;amp;version=4.5&amp;amp;mask=search_form_islamhs_advanced.xed&amp;amp;start=0&amp;amp;fl=id,returnId&amp;amp;rows=1&amp;amp;XSL.Style=browse&amp;amp;origrows=25 al-Naʿʿal, Saʾin al-Din Muhammad b. al-Anjab: Mashyakhat al-Naʿʿal al-Baghdadi. Takhrij al-hafiz Rashid al-Din Muhammad b. ʿAbd al-ʿAzim  al-Mundhiri. Baghdad 1975 al-Nawawi: Al-Ijaz fi sharh sunan Abi Dawud al-Sijistani. wa-fi muqaddimat tahqiqihi Tuhfat al-talibin fi tarjamat al-imam Muhyi al-Din tasnif ʿAlaʾ al-Din ʿAli b. Ibrahim b. al-ʿAttar. ʿAmman 2007 al-Razi, Abu ʿAbd Allah Muhammad b. Ahmad b. Ibrahim: Mashyakhat al-shaykh al-ajall Abi ʿAbd Allah Muhammad b. Ahmad b. Ibrahim al-Razi al-maʿruf bi-Ibn al-Hattab wa-thabat masmuʿatihi bi-intiqaʾ al-shaykh al-ajall al-imam al-ʿalim al-hafiz Abi Tahir Ahmad b. Muhammad b. Ahmad al-Silafi. Al-Riyad 1994 al-Samʿani, Abu Saʿd ʿAbd al-Karim b. Muhammad b. Mansur al-Tamimi: Al-Muntakhab min muʿjam shuyukh al-imam al-hafiz Abi Saʿd ʿAbd al-Karim b. Muhammad b. Mansur al-Samʿani al-Tamimi. Al-Riyad 1996 al-Subki, Taj al-Din ʿAbd al-Wahhab b. ʿAli: Muʿjam al-shuyukh. Takhrij Shams al-Din al-Salihi. Bayrut 2004</summary></entry></feed>